<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The particular state of the government of the Emperour, Ferdinand the Second As it was at his decease in the yeere 1636. Translated out of Latin by R.W.</title>
            <title>Status particularis regiminis S.C. Majestatis Ferdinandi II. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101977</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837780</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The particular state of the government of the Emperour, Ferdinand the Second As it was at his decease in the yeere 1636. Translated out of Latin by R.W.</title>
                  <title>Status particularis regiminis S.C. Majestatis Ferdinandi II. English.</title>
                  <author>R. W., fl. 1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. G[riffin] for Thomas Nichols, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Bible in Popes head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Status particularis regiminis S.C. Majestatis Ferdinandi II.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹ B-K⁴ L² .</note>
                  <note>"The state of the imperiall-court of the Emperour Ferdinand the Second" has separate title page with imprint "London, printed by Anne Griffin. 1637"; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of the edition with Anne Griffin's name in the imprint of the first title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferdinand, Holy Roman Emperor, --  II, 1578-1637 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Holy Roman Empire --  Court and courtiers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Holy Roman Empire --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE PARTICVLAR STATE Of the Government of the Emperour, FERDINAND THE SECOND As it was at his deceaſe in the yeere 1636.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tranſlated out of Latin by</hi> R. W.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device?</figDesc>
                     <q>VERITAS FILIA TEMPORIS</q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Nichols,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the ſigne of the Bible in Popes head Alley, 1637.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:2"/>
                  <head>THE PARTICVLAR STATE OF The Government of the late <hi>Emperour,</hi> FERDINAND the ſecond, &amp;c. <hi>As it was in the yeere,</hi> 1636.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>Of the reaſons for which the Emperour</hi> FERDINAND, <hi>the ſecond, hath alwaies kept his Court at</hi> Vienna.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N treating of the State, of the late Emperour FER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DINAND the ſecond, It is firſt of all to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; that his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, from the beginning of his raigne to the end of his life, did ever keepe his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reſidence in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Vienna;</hi> as well for the commodious Scituation, and pleaſantneſſe of the place; plenty of foode, and all other neceſſaries for man; and
<pb facs="tcp:2122:3"/>
the adjoyning Forreſts and Woods, moſt fit for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and other neighbouring places of pleaſure; the chiefe of which are, <hi>Brater, Begelhoff, Newgebew, Caterburg, Eberſdorff, Laxemburg, Wolckers dorff, Orth, Cloſter Newburg,</hi> or the Monaſtery of <hi>Neoburg, Newſtat,</hi> &amp;c. As alſo (chiefly, ſince theſe long, and yet continued, warres in <hi>Germany,)</hi> by reaſon of the ſtrength of the City, and that his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty being there was in a manner ſafely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed by the reſt of his hereditary Kingdomes, &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, from whence hee might, in caſe of need, with more conveniency derive aſſiſtance: And laſtly, for the benefit of the two navigable Rivers of <hi>Ehu</hi> and <hi>Danube,</hi> by which all neceſſaries for the Imperiall Court, may from other places of the <hi>German</hi> Empire and from <hi>Italy,</hi> be the more eaſily furniſhed and brought thither.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>Of the Scituation, circuit, and fortification of</hi> Vienna; <hi>of the</hi> Danube; <hi>of the Gariſon, Suburbs, Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Biſhop, the Vniverſity, Civill and Politique govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Lieutenant; and of the Caſtle of</hi> Vienna; <hi>in which the Emperour keepes his Court.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> is the Metropolis of the Lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> as the Towne of <hi>Lintz</hi> is of the upper. In both which places now, almoſt every yeare, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (when neceſſity requires) there are often in one yeare held Aſſemblies of each province, in which as to the lawfull Prince and Lord of the Country, when hee doth fairely aske it, are often granted and preſented by the ſubjects many hundred thouſand crownes to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty.</p>
                     <p>The City it ſelfe is ſeated in ſomewhat a pleaſant
<pb facs="tcp:2122:3"/>
plaine, and in a ſoile which is naturally moſt fruitfull and good for Corne and Wine, and all other kinde of Food and fruites, upon the bankes of the <hi>Danube;</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed it be but a branch of the maine <hi>Danube,</hi> yet at the ſeaſon of the yeare, when the River is high, it is capable of good ordinary veſſels. But when the River decreaſeth, the ſhips are forced to ſtay above at <hi>Nuſdorff,</hi> a league from the City, and ſometimes two leagues higher, at the Monaſtery of <hi>Newburg.</hi> About halfe a quarter of a German league from the City, towards <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> are likewiſe three other ſtreames, and for the moſt part, large and navigeable armes of the great River <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube;</hi> over which are layd five bridges, which for the greater ſecurity of the City, if need require, may be taken downe.</p>
                     <p>On the South ſide of the City there is a little River, or rather a Torrent, of the name of the City, called <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna;</hi> which riſeth out of the Weſterne mountaines, and is ſubject to ſudden overflowing by raine and Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waters<hi>:</hi> it drives ſome Mills, and falls into the <hi>Danube,</hi> not farre from the Towne ditch. Towards the South and North, it runnes like an arme of the <hi>Dannbe,</hi> and on the Weſt, it leaves behind it the hills and mountaines looking towards the Vpper <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The City is in compaſſe about halfe a German league, and is beautified with many faire and ſpacious places, and markets, and with other leſſe, and it hath ſome faire ſtreets, with many goodly and ſtately buildings, which notwithſtanding are commonly more for ſhew than conveniency.</p>
                     <p>For the fortification of the City, it will ſuffice in this place briefly to declare, that it is ſtrengthned and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with ſixe principall Gates, and ten great Bulwarkes;
<pb facs="tcp:2122:4"/>
The greateſt part of which Bulwarks, and ſome of them at the expence of the Empire, are built up a good height of Bricke, and filld within with earth; and ſome alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt and South, (whereby the City might be the more defenſible) have good Caſamats, well raiſed and repaired. About ten yeares ſince, his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty cauſed a very great intire Bulwarke to be raiſed of earth, almoſt right over againſt the Imperiall Court, or Archducall Caſtle, for the greater ſecurity thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Caſtle heretofore, had beene in that place but weakely fortified. Two yeares ſince, the former Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, which looketh towards the South, and towards the Weſt, was ſtrongly new built.</p>
                     <p>The Scottiſh Bulwarke caſt up of earth onely, is now well lined with a ſtrong wall, and made equall to the reſt of the Bulwarkes.</p>
                     <p>Towards the Eaſt is a gate, commonly called <hi>Struben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor:</hi> Towards the South, the <hi>Carnithian</hi> gate; and the Caſtle gate, called, <hi>Burgthor;</hi> towards the Weſt, the South gate, and the new gate; towards the North, the gate of the red Tower, called in Dutch, <hi>der Roche Thum:</hi> The Caſtle gate, the <hi>Carinthian</hi> gate, the New gate, and the gate called <hi>Strubenthor,</hi> are the ſtrongeſt, all arched, very high and ſtately, with large paſſages; the other two are are onely Towers.</p>
                     <p>To compaſſe the City from the Gate called <hi>Struben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> to goe to the gate of the red Tower, you muſt paſſe firſt neare a Bulwarke built of Free-ſtone, with two high and battel'd Caſamats, the higher of which doth almoſt touch the Dominicans Temple, the height whereof exceeds this Bulwarke and Caſamats.</p>
                     <p>Thence you come to another Bulwarke ſtrongly covered with a Bricke-wall, which (as the former) is
<pb facs="tcp:2122:4"/>
environed with reaſonable deepe ditches.</p>
                     <p>From this Bulwark, on the left ſide of the towne, are ſeene ſome little and low double Walls, reaching to an outward Gate; but on the right hand, neare the towne, doth runne the <hi>Danube,</hi> on which is built a bridge of wood, commonly called <hi>Schlagbruck.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This outward Gate leads to a broad ſtreet, where the City is ſomewhat naked<hi>:</hi> For on the left hand there are very low Walls onely, and on the right hand nothing but the <hi>Danube,</hi> which one may ſometimes ride over; and ſome fortifications, which are built on the bankes thereof, towards the red Tower, and further towards the other outward gate, neere which the ſtreet is narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. From this Gate, the City is encompaſſed on the left hand, with long ſtrong high Walls, on which theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle watch-houſes are built, which reach to the Armory, and thence to the next Bulwarke. It hath alſo a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge. The third Bulwarke is great and ſtately, (but wants ditches and water) and a good part of the middle of the upper Wall is fallen downe and wants repaire.</p>
                     <p>Thence to the New gate, which hath broad but ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ditches, without water, <hi>Henry Matthew,</hi> the elder Count of <hi>Turne,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1619. would have planted a petard to this Gate, and with his horſe which then lodg'd at <hi>Eberſdorff,</hi> attempted to take the City.</p>
                     <p>Thence to the fourth Bulwark, which likewiſe wants mending and repaire. From this Bulwarke, the Rampire is very high, with a little Wall upon it, towards the Scotch gate, and there the Towne-ditch is very deepe, but without water. Thence the ſame kind of Rampire and ditch extends unto the next fift Bulwarke. This Bulwarke was onely caſt up of earth, but now of late is built up from the ground with a Bricke wall, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb facs="tcp:2122:5"/>
to an orderly forme and proportion, and by that meanes the City is the better fortified in that place. The <hi>Bohemian</hi> foote Regiment of <hi>Tieffenbach,</hi> who were then commanded by the ſaid elder Count of <hi>Turne,</hi> remained not farre from the City in a Village called <hi>Hoernals,</hi> if the deſigne had taken effect and had not beene diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a Patriot, by this Bulwark ſhould have entred and taken the City.</p>
                     <p>This ſame high Rampire lined with Bricke walls, in the ditches, at that place very deepe, but without water, paſſeth along towards and behind the ſixt Bulwarke, over which the preſent Governour of the Towne, <hi>Baron Lobell,</hi> hath cauſed a little garden, with a houſe of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be built, according to the bravery of the time. And becauſe this Bulwarke was lately renewed and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reformed than the other, it excels the reſt in beauty. Behind, it hath a Caſamat with Bricke walls, like the former. Thence the Rampire with a low, meane, and in ſome places but a weake Wall, built thereon, extends it ſelfe, even to the Imperiall Court, or Archducal Caſtle, where by the raiſing of the outward highway the ditches are made deeper.</p>
                     <p>Thence to the Caſtle gate, in Dutch <hi>das Burgthor,</hi> where ſtands the vaſt ſeventh Bulwarke of earth, which behinde hath a leſſe Bulwarke alſo, like a Caſamat, not built high, but compleatly walled.</p>
                     <p>On this ſide a <hi>Bohemian</hi> ſouldier, under the command of the elder Count of <hi>Turne,</hi> did ſhoot ſome bullets, from the ſuburbs of St. <hi>Vbris,</hi> into the Imperiall Court or Archducall Caſtle, and even into the great Chamber of the Knights and Nobles, and into the Antichamber; and drove his Imperiall Majeſty, then King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> out of his owne Chamber.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:5"/>
From thence the Rampire, with a Wall above, and Fortifications below, extends it ſelfe with very deepe ditches almoſt to the <hi>Carinthian</hi> gate; before which is a ſtrong, great, ſtately and faire Bulwarke, all of Bricke, the eight in number, joyning to the Gate, behind which and above the Gate, there is a Caſamat rayſed. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Gate, the Captaine of the City watch hath a faire lodging.</p>
                     <p>From this <hi>Carinthian</hi> gate, inſtead of the Rampire, are Bricke walls, almoſt of one height with the Bulwarkes, the ditches are there of good depth, but (as the others) without water.</p>
                     <p>Then followes the ninth, which as the former is a very ſtately Bulwark; with an Aquaduct into the towne, and hitherto the ditches are dry; but about this Bulwarke, the Aquaduct, which ſerves both to bring in neceſſary water, and in time of need, furniſh the dry ditches with water, and rendereth them ſomewhat wet and mariſh, but from the corner thereof and lower, they are deeper, and more fill'd with water.</p>
                     <p>From thence runnes the Rampire, to the tenth Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, commonly called <hi>Obere Stuben Paſtey,</hi> which is moſt exquiſitely faire, large, lofty, and ſtrongly faced with bricke, and the corners of Freeſtone, with a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent inſcription in golden letters, on tables of ſtone. This Bulwarke was built and perfected by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt.</p>
                     <p>Theſe three laſt Bulwarks are of one height, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led alike, and each of them have a ſeverall inſcription, with golden letters, in Tables of ſtone.</p>
                     <p>Of theſe ten Bulwarks of the City, three onely ſtand in water, which is drawne from the <hi>Danube,</hi> and ſome certaine veines which runne into the City, and all the reſt are dry.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:6"/>
The ditches of the City are are very unequall and unlike.</p>
                     <p>About the City are great and ſpacious ſuburbs, in which are divers faire and pleaſant gardens, with houſes of pleaſure, and ſtore of other conſiderable dwellings, whereof many, eſpecially before the Caſtle gate called <hi>das Burgthor,</hi> and the <hi>Carinthian</hi> gate: towards St. <hi>Vlrics,</hi> and the little River of <hi>Vienna;</hi> for about three hundred paces together, as well to enlarge the way and ſtreets, as for the greater ſafety of the City, were purpoſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed; and others a few yeeres ſince were burnt by accident.</p>
                     <p>The garriſon of this Towne conſiſts at this preſent of about one thouſand foote, in eight companies, of which the <hi>Baron of Lobel</hi> Collonell, is Captaine, and one of the Emperours Councells of Warre, and Vice Preſident of that Counſell. About ſome eight yeeres ſince the armes, which had beene taken from the Citizens when <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke Leopald</hi> was Governour of the Citty in the yeare 1619. were reſtored unto them againe, the Citizens being for the moſt part Proteſtants, and there being a ſuſpition conceived of ſome ſecret intelligence betwixt them and the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> but eſpecially with the elder Count of <hi>Turne:</hi> The Magiſtrates fearing ſome attempt of the Proteſtants againſt the Roman Catholicks, had cauſed the Proteſtants to bee diſarmed.</p>
                     <p>The Burgmaſter, by the command of his Imperiall Majeſty, as lawfull Prince of this Archdutchy of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> heretofore did chooſe out and raiſe fower Companies of foote of Citizens, of three hundred a peece. Theſe ſelected men have beene uſed on urgent neceſſities for the defence of the City, as was lately practiſed in the time of the laſt <hi>Hungarian</hi> ſeditions and rebellions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:2122:6"/>
the direction of <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> For when part of a garriſon was ſent to defend the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Presbury,</hi> the ſelected Citizens were forced to ſerve foure moneths together, for the defence of the Towne. The pay of the garriſon is ſixe florins a man by the moneth, but for want of due payment they are often ſeene to beg in the ſtreets.</p>
                     <p>In time of warre and danger, ſome Cornets of horſe uſe to be taken into the ſuburbs; at other times the guard remaines unaltered.</p>
                     <p>Some thinke that the City of <hi>Vienna</hi> is ſo populous, that it containes, within and without, ſome threeſcore thouſand ſoules, but the certaine number is hard to bee knowne.</p>
                     <p>The ſuburbs on the other ſide of the <hi>Danube</hi> are inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by Iewes, as an Iland a part, and in the Towne they have a place of commerce, where by day they ſell their commodities: but it is not lawfull for them to lie all night in Towne. But becauſe they bring great profits to the Imperiall Court, and for other cauſes and reaſons, they are not onely tollerated in this City, but they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy many great priviledges and liberties.</p>
                     <p>The Evangelicall Lutheran Religion, or the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Augsburg,</hi> being heretofore brought into this City, did afterwards ſo increaſe under the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond; that the ſaid Evangelicks, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other privelidges, had the exerciſe of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the City it ſelfe, even in the Minimes Temple, at the Provinciall Houſe. And although the Emperour <hi>Rodolph</hi> the ſecond, and before him <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt, did reſolve to their power, to aboliſh the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that religion; and began likewiſe a great refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and advanced the buſineſſe ſo farre, that under
<pb facs="tcp:2122:7"/>
the Emperour <hi>Rodolph</hi> the ſecond, the Evangelicall ſtate of Lower <hi>Auſtria</hi> loſt the exerciſe of their religion in the City of <hi>Vienna;</hi> and it ſeemed as if an univerſall deforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a totall ſuppreſſion, and extirpation of all the Evangelicks, in thoſe Countries, would have followed: Yet the Emperour <hi>Matthias</hi> the firſt, for divers great cauſes did moſt graciouſly grant the Evangelicall ſtate of Lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the exerciſe of their religion in the Village called <hi>Hoernals,</hi> about a quarter of a German league from the City, and granted them his high Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall and Archducall Protection; notwithſtanding the Catholickes, eſpecially the Cleargy, (whom the exerciſe of that religion did vehemently offend) perſwaded themſelves, that the ſermons of Cardinal <hi>Clozel,</hi> would have enduced the Emperour againe, to prohibit the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Evangelicks at <hi>Hoernals:</hi> And that he would not permit them Evangelicall Matrimony, nor the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments of Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
                     <p>But when the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond tooke the raines of the Roman Empire, and had taken the City of <hi>Prag;</hi> a Prieſt did ſeriouſly inculcate to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that whereas ſince the ſtates of the Evangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces had beene permitted the exerciſe of their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Village of <hi>Hoernals,</hi> by the Emperour <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> the firſt, they had ſo multiplyed that in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation there were ſometimes twenty, thirty, even forty, or fifty thouſand perſons, and therefore hee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly petitioned that the exerciſe of that religion might be aboliſhed by publike command. And thereupon it came to paſſe, that a reformation of religion was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d in the City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> by an Imperiall Mandate; and the exerciſe of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> confeſſion in the Village
<pb facs="tcp:2122:7"/>
of <hi>Hoernals</hi> (which was afterwards given to the Cathedrall Church of St. <hi>Steven</hi> in <hi>Vienna)</hi> was quite ſuppreſſed, upon a pretext that the Baron <hi>Helmhardt Iorger,</hi> who was then in priſon at <hi>Lintz,</hi> had no right of patrinage in that Village, and all the Evangelicall Preachers were forbidden to enter the City upon grievous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But yet in <hi>Auſtria</hi> they were ſuffred, for their perſons, as heretofore; and ſome of the Citizens and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants had leave to goe out of the Towne, unto Sermons and Sacraments after the Evangelicall manner, at <hi>Intzerrdorff,</hi> belonging to the Lord <hi>Geyer</hi> of <hi>Oſterburg,</hi> a Mile from the City.</p>
                     <p>But at the laſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1627. his Imperiall Maieſty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely required all Eccleſiaſticall Evangelicks by publike Imperiall, and Archducall Proclamations and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates, to void by a certaine time, all the Country of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and all other his Imperiall Majeſties hereditary Dominions, with prohibition under his highneſſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and unpardonable puniſhents, never to returne, or to remaine there upon any termes.</p>
                     <p>In Eccleſiaſtically matters the City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the Biſhop who hath ſpirituall juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over all the Biſhoppricke of <hi>Vienna.</hi> And the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop hath his Officiat alwaies in <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Cathedrall Church, which is dedicated to St. <hi>Steven</hi> is of a coſtly, great, high and large building, ſet off on one ſide, with a very high ſpired and excellent faire ſteeple, in which there is a very great and goodly Bell. A like ſteeple was on the other ſide begun and brought to ſome perfection, but was never finiſhed; this (they ſay) the Biſhop will perfect, and make it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the other, and it is thought that in foure yeares ſpace it may be finiſhed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:8"/>
The preſent Biſhop hath likewiſe cauſed all the old Biſhops houſe to be pul'd downe, and is building a large magnificent Pallace in the place, to which purpoſe hee hath obtained of the Emperour, a hundred thouſand Rixdollers, which was the price of the Duke of <hi>Meckel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs</hi> reconciliation.</p>
                     <p>This Church was raiſed to a Cathedrall by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond, at the mediation of the Emperour <hi>Fredericke</hi> the third. The Biſhops revenew amounts but to 8000. florins; which is but 1200 pounds ſterling. The preſent Biſhops name is <hi>Antony,</hi> who hath gained the Title of Prince from the Emperour: And hee holds beſipes the Biſhoppricke, the wealthy Abby of <hi>Crembſmun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> of St. <hi>Bennets</hi> Order in Upper <hi>Auſtria.</hi> He is alſo a Privy Councellour to his Imperiall Majeſty, and the firſt of the Counſell. His predeceſſour was Cardinall <hi>Clozel,</hi> who dyed at <hi>Vienna,</hi> in the yeare 1630. There are ſixteene Cannons of this Cathedrall, but by reaſon of the ſmall revenue of the Church, their ſtipends are but ſlender. They all dwell about the Cathedrall.</p>
                     <p>There are alſo divers other Churches and Cloyſters within and without this City.</p>
                     <p>The Emperour <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond founded the Univerſity at <hi>Vienna,</hi> in the yeare 1237. and indued it with very great priviledges and immunities, which were afterwards renewed, and amplified by <hi>Albert</hi> the third of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, about the yeare 1622. gave this Academy to the Ieſuits, with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning and appendant Burſes and Colledges or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, where now they teach and breed their ſchollers. His Majeſty alſo granted them the liberty of prefeſſing Theology and Philoſophy, but upon condition that the
<pb facs="tcp:2122:8"/>
chaire ſhould be free for any of the <hi>Dominicans, Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi> or <hi>Minimes</hi> to profeſſe or diſpute.</p>
                     <p>The Lawyers and Phiſicians continue their ancient combination, and every ſixe moneths, they chooſe a new Rector. When they thinke fit to call a Counſell for the good of themſelves, or any other of the united perſons of the Univerſity; it is choſen, and conſiſts of ſixteene of thoſe faculties. The Rector of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity hath juriſdiction over all the perſons and members of the Vniverſity.</p>
                     <p>The civil government of the City is ordered by the Senate, which conſiſts of eighteene Citizens and Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to whom all buſineſſes are propounded, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the particular or common good of the Citizens or City, and by them they are deliberated. The chiefe of theſe is the Burgmaſter. In criminall matters, the Burg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter hath his Aſſeſſors and Aſſiſtants. But the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill government is not abſolutely in the Senate, but doth depend on the Lieutenant of the Lower <hi>Auſtria.</hi> And at all Colledges, and conſultations of the Senators, an Imperiall Miniſter is alwaies preſent in perſon.</p>
                     <p>The Office of Lieutenant is now exerciſed by Baron <hi>Sigfrid Chriſtopher Preunez,</hi> one of his Imperiall Majeſties Privy Counſell, and preſident of the government of Lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> who hath chiefe cognizans in matters which concerne the Cities, and civill government; and in the abſence of his Imperiall Majeſty the government is ſolely in him.</p>
                     <p>The Arſenall of <hi>Vienna</hi> is compleatly furniſhed, not onely with ſhips and Veſſels uſefull for the place; but alſo with Armes, all warlike preparation, and with great and ſmall Ordnance, which are there kept. The preſent Maſter of the which is Count <hi>Xantelier,</hi> by Nation a <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine;</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:9"/>
but becauſe his Father brought him to the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Court when he was yong and he hath long perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his office well, he is now eſteemed a German.</p>
                     <p>The Court of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or the Archducall Caſtle; in Dutch <hi>das Burg;</hi> hath no ſingular ſplendor or magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficens, and is ſomewhat ſtraight for ſo great a Prince and ſtately a Court. It containes in it a great Court, on one ſide whereof, is the Imperiall Chancery; on the other ſide is the Inner Caſtle, or the lodgings of the Emperour; and on the third ſide is the Rampire of the City, with a gallery upon it. And on the fourth ſide is the new Caſtle commonly called <hi>die Newburg,</hi> and the Court in the midſt.</p>
                     <p>In this Imperiall Pallace there is a Waldrope, and a Gallery with ſeverall chambers, which they call the Treaſury, wherein are kept great ſtore of all ſorts of moſt precious variety of gold, precious ſtones, and pearle; with pictures and other things of curious worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, and with many rare pieces of nature and art, worth many millions. Amongſt other things, which are moſt worthy of note, is the Imperiall Crowne and Scepter, and the Imperiall Globe; moſt richly adorned with gold, and rich orientall Dyamonds, valued at a mill on of gold; made by the Emperour <hi>Rodolph</hi> for his owne ſacred perſon. Item a round globe, ſeven ſpanne in compaſſe cut out of one intire Agate, with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of IEHOVAH, made by nature it ſelfe in darker caracters. Then a Vnicornes Horne of twelve or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene ſpannes long of which two laſt, the valew is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable, becauſe their like in forme, beauty, quality, and quantity, are not to be found in the whole world. To this ſame Pallace in which the Emperour himſelfe doth lodge, there belong two pleaſant gardens, the one
<pb facs="tcp:2122:9"/>
bigger than the other, into which his Imperiall Majeſty hath an eary an commodious paſſage out of his owne lodgings.</p>
                     <p>In this Court of the Caſtle, called the <hi>Burgplatz,</hi> neare the Emperours lodgings, is a company of Foot, and at the entry to the inner Caſtle, under the very gate, neere the Drawbridge, ten of the Guard, called <hi>Frabauten,</hi> doe commonly watch; and keepe their ſtation there all day, with their Halberds, but at night they draw up the bridge, and watch within, untill they bee relieved by others of their fellowes. And before the chambers of the Emperour and Empreſſe, there are other Guards which waite with Javelins, called <hi>Hartſchierer,</hi> and theſe are ever ready to attend and follow the Emperour whereſoever hee goeth, as well in Iourneys as when hee goes to walke, as the ordinary horſe guard of his body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>Of the perſon of the Emperour</hi> Ferdinand <hi>the ſecond, and of his Imperiall vertues and qualities, his devotion and piety, his workes of humiliation, and of his diſpatch of buſineſſe, recreations and meales.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, was ſonne to the Archduke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Auſtrin,</hi> who lived at <hi>Gratz,</hi> and Grandchild to the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt; and had as his heredetary countries the Dutchies of <hi>Stiria Carinthia,</hi> and <hi>Carniola,</hi> with other appendent Provinces. But when the two Lines of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> family; that of the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and that of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Archduke of <hi>Inf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruck,</hi> were both failed. And that the Archduke <hi>Albert,</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:10"/>
who lived in the <hi>Low-countriess,</hi> was growne old and weake, and had reteined the government of the <hi>Auſtria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Provinces; His Imperiall Majeſty, partly by ſucceſſion, and partly by agreement and conſent, (but chiefly, by his being choſen and Crowned King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> which was a ſtrong foundation of his future greatneſſe) obtained the poſſeſſion of all thoſe Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And after this on the 28. of <hi>Auguſt, Anno</hi> 1619. (the Emperour <hi>Matthias</hi> the firſt being dead,) he was elected and crowned Emperour at <hi>Francfurt</hi> on the <hi>Maine;</hi> At which time raigned theſe Kings and Princes in divers Kingdomes of <hi>Europe,</hi> IAMES <hi>the firſt, King of Great Brittaine;</hi> LEVVIS <hi>the thirteene, King of France;</hi> PHILIP <hi>the third King of Spaine;</hi> CHRISTIAN <hi>the fourth, King of Denmarke;</hi> GVSTAVVS ADOLPHVS, <hi>King of Sweden;</hi> SIGISMVND <hi>the third, King of Poland;</hi> and in the Eaſt, the <hi>Sultan Oſman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now for the perſon of his Imperiall Majeſty, he was of fifty nine yeares of age, of a midling ſtature and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent, of an excellent complexion, ſtrong and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; his haire and beard ſomewhat gray, of a gracefull preſence; of a kinde, meeke, bounteous, and liberall djſpoſition, and of a ſingular underſtanding, eloquence and memory; temperate in meate and drinke, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in ſleepe; hee ſeldome went to bed till ten at night, and ſometimes not till one; and he ordinarily did riſe at foure in the morning, and on his bended knees commend himſelfe by prayer to God. On feſtivall and ſolemne daies principally on the Apoſtles daies, he did confeſſe and heare Maſſe. The thurſday before Eaſter he uſed to receive the holy Sacrament from the hands of the Popes Nuncio, in company of the Empreſſe, the King, and Queene of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Archduke, and the
<pb facs="tcp:2122:10"/>
Archdutcheſſe, and other principall perſons of the Court, according to the rule of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Before his Imperiall Majeſty went to Church, hee did appoint two Maſſes to be ſaid in the chappell or cloſet, one for himſelfe, another for his late wife; who was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to <hi>Maximilian</hi> the preſent Duke of <hi>Bavaria;</hi> and ſometimes at the ſame time hee did receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<hi>:</hi> And then he went to Church, where hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly did heare a Sermon in Dutch of one of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, who is the ordinary preacher of the Court, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an houre long. The Sermon ended, high Maſſe is celebrated with great devotion, and moſt ſweet Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, which laſts at leaſt an houre. After dinner he did uſe to heare an <hi>Italian</hi> Sermon by the ordinary Court <hi>Italian</hi> Preacher, and after that the veſpers, which are ſung with great ſolemnity. And in this manner his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty ſpent almoſt the whole Sunday or holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. And ſometimes he did viſit other Churches, both within &amp; without the City; as the <hi>Dominicans</hi> the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> or the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> and in theſe Colledges and Convents he ſometimes did dine.</p>
                     <p>In the time of Advent, his Imperiall Majeſty did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly riſe very early, to frequent certaine Mattins, like ſinging Maſſes, called <hi>Rorate;</hi> becauſe at his entry is ſung the ſaid <hi>Rorate coeli,</hi> which is followed with Muſicke of inſtruments and voices, almoſt an houres ſpace, which time the people imploy in their prayers and devotions. The ſame Office is likewiſe ſolemnely celebrated with great concourſe in all the Churches.</p>
                     <p>During the time of Lent, his Imperiall Majeſty was moſt diligently wont to heare Sermons, in his Court chappell, and in the <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Church which is neare the Caſtle; and on Holidaies in the Chappell of the
<pb facs="tcp:2122:11"/>
Minimes, eſpecially in the time of the penitentiall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions; and every day in Lent are ſung the Veſpers at large in the Imperiall Oratory.</p>
                     <p>On Maundy thurſday before noone, his Imperiall Majeſty publikely, and before all there preſent, did waſh the feet of thirty poore men, then feede them and ſerve them in his owne perſon, at table. After he gave to every one a gowne, and a piece of gold of the valew of a double <hi>Hungarian</hi> ducat.</p>
                     <p>At the ſame day and time, in another place apart, the Empreſſe performes the ſame, out of humility, to thirty poore women.</p>
                     <p>The laſt Sunday before Eaſter his Imperiall Majeſty was wont to viſit all the Churches of the Towne on foot after the Catholicke <hi>Roman</hi> manner, and to pray before the Tombes erected in them. This laſt yeare a coach did eaſe his feet of that pennance.</p>
                     <p>During the weeke of holy Croſſe, beginning from Sunday to the feaſt of the <hi>Aſcenſion of Chriſt,</hi> his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſty was uſed to be at the accuſtomed Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at which this yeare his weakeneſſe hath not ſuffered him to be preſent.</p>
                     <p>On <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, when the great Proceſſion is ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated, his Imperall Majeſty did uſe to aſſiſt with all the Court on foot, bare headed, and to pray on bended knees at all the altars by the way. And the ſunday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he was uſed to attend the Proceſſion of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits: and the next ſunday to bee preſent with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion at the generall Proceſſion, which is very popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and continues from morning untill noone.</p>
                     <p>For this cauſe the Popes Nuncio Cardinall <hi>Palatto</hi> in his relation made to Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> the eight; doth teſtifie (to the great commendation of his Imperiall Majeſty,)
<pb facs="tcp:2122:11"/>
the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond may well be ſtiled a holy Prince, a man after Gods owne heart, as was King <hi>David,</hi> and that for the candor of his conſcience, and his firme faith in God, the protection of the Almighty hath beene ſo conſtant, on his Imperiall perſon, that as the Lords annoynted he never hath or could be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or hurt by any. As plainely appeareth by his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall magnanimity, in the very beginning of his raigne, and ſome following yeeres after, when the three Regal Offices and Counſellors of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> being throwne out of the window at Prag, in the yeare 1618. the 25. of <hi>May</hi> (the Emperour <hi>Matthas</hi> the firſt being yet alive) all his hereditary Provinces and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys were deſtroyed with fire and ſword, and his ſacred perſon (as it were) in the midſt of his enemies, having nothing remaining, but onely the City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> it was not poſſible to force him from his Reſidence, but on the contrary hee was alwaies moſt miraculouſly preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by God.</p>
                     <p>The ſame Nuncio reports alſo, that his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, hath ſaid, in greateſt dangers; that the divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence had abundantly manifeſted its ſtrength and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in his ſacred perſon, above the reach and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of man.</p>
                     <p>And for matters of religion or conſcience, when his Imperiall Maieſty did depute a Counſellour or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner to that end, he did not precipitate a ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but firſt remit all to his Confeſſour, who is moſt acute and prudent father, whoſe counſell and a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Imperiall Majeſty (as the ſheep his ſheepheard) did conſtantly follow with a willing and ready mind and heart; and to cleare himſelfe from all ſcruples of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, he did referre unto him all, even the leaſt things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:12"/>
On other daies, (except the Lords day) having heard two Maſſes and diſpatched his private conſultations, for every day, or at leaſt every other day, hee did hold a Counſell, unleſſe there were ſomething of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſpatch, his Imperiall Majeſty uſed to goe out of towne to take the aire, or to hunt (in which kinde of exerciſe he did moſt delight) and commonly returned not till night: whence the proverb grew, that his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty in three things was indefatigable; to wit, In devotion, in counſell, and in hunting. And although ſometimes he did returne ſomewhat late and tired from hunting; yet did hee never refuſe or forbeare to ſigne with his owne hand forty, fifty; or threeſcore or more ſeverall things at one time, concerning the buſineſſe of the Empire, and other matters, and without the leaſt ſhew of diſpleaſure or impatience; and then hee did ſit downe to meate. So that his Imperiall Majeſty did never returne from counſell, from hunting, or from au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (as they terme it,) without preſcribing or ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſomewhat, or reading memorials, or being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe imployed. And foraſmuch as his Imperiall Majeſty by reaſon of the many buſineſſes of the Empire, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of great conſequence, could not himſelfe read the leaſt part of them; if there was any thing preſented to himſelfe, or to the maſter of his chamber, hee did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it to be ſent by a waiter or huiſher of the chamber unto the Counſell proper for the buſineſſe, that it might be ſpeedily diſpatched.</p>
                     <p>His Imperiall Majeſty was moſt of all delighted in hunting (as is ſaid) and in Muſicke; and did keepe all kind of dogges, and ſtrange birds, for hunting and haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. Of Huntſmen and Falcners, hee had about 150. But beſides theſe, his Imperiall Majeſty, in all his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary
<pb facs="tcp:2122:12"/>
Kingdomes, and Provinces, had a chiefe Huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with divers others, and dogges without number.</p>
                     <p>He did uſe a piece very skilfully; but his chiefeſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was to mooſe his game, and with his owne hand to kill wild boares, which he afterwards ſent for preſents of honour to forraine Ambaſſadours and Agents, and to the officers of the Court. And he was wont to keepe a catalogue of the annuall number of the Deere he killed, and ſent to the Electour of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Imperiall Majeſty was likewiſe very curious to get exquiſite Muſitians, and to theſe two kinds of men, Muſitians and Huntſmen, he did give very liberally, and ſpend much money on them. Muſicke, he ſaid, is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and fit for the praiſe and honour of the Almighty; and to make the heart of man merry.</p>
                     <p>His Imperiall Majeſty did ordinarily dine in his Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, but moſt commonly ſup with the Empreſſe. Two yeares ſince, his Imperiall Majeſty, with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, King and Queene of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Archduke and Archdutcheſſe, on ſolemne and great feaſts, (as at <hi>Chriſtinas, Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide,)</hi> uſed to eat in publike in the Chamber of the Knights and Nobles, before a great multitude; where there was commonly moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Muſicke of Inſtruments.</p>
                     <p>The Emperours Table is uſually attended by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries of the chamber, Sewers, Cupbearers, and ſuch like Officers, and ſometimes alſo by Princes, Earles, and Barrons of the Empire, who having waited about an houres ſpace, withdraw themſelves. For no Prince is admitted to fit at the Emperours table in his Court at <hi>Vienna;</hi> but elſewhere, and in the Country, hee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, though ſeldome at his reſidence, cauſeth ſome to ſit at table with him, according as they are great and
<pb facs="tcp:2122:13"/>
eminent either by their birth and quality, or in his grace and favour.</p>
                     <p>It is worth the obſerving, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the elder Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> being reconciled to the Emperour, preſented the towell to his Imperiall Majeſty after waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and after waited bareheaded; but when he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his inveſtiture and feudalities from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and ſtood likewiſe bareheaded before the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall table; the Emperour conſidering it, would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thereof; and thereupon by the chiefe Marſhall of his Court, (which then was the Earle of <hi>Lozenſtein,)</hi> commanded him to put on his hat, which he did; and withall to ſit at the table with him, which he did alſo in the Caſtle of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When his Imperiall Majeſty ſits at the table with the Empreſſe, in ſtead of Noblemen, Knights, and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Imperiall Ladies and maids of the Empreſſe ſerve at the table, and then there is moſt exquiſite Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke; otherwiſe there is no muſicke at dinner, unleſſe it be on feſtivall and holydaies.</p>
                     <p>The meates which are ſerved on the Imperiall board, are neither coſtly nor dainty, nor any way ſuperfluous in ſplendor or magnificence, for ſo great a Prince.</p>
                     <p>According to the time and occaſion there are Ieſters, which make ſport and tell merry tales. Amongſt theſe <hi>Ionas</hi> is the prime for ſudden jeſts, but they are never ſo free as when the Emperour is abroad, or hunting.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:13"/>
                     <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>Of the manner of the Emperours going to the Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, of his attendants and of the carriage of the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours and Agents at thoſe times, and how his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is ſerved returning from Church or Chappell, and what he then uſed to doe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHen his Imperiall Majeſty goes to the Church, the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> being preſent, goes next before him, in a Coach alone; and then followes his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty, either alone, or with the Empreſſe. When the Queene of <hi>Hungary</hi> is preſent, the Empreſſe and ſhe, and the Archdutcheſſe are moſt commonly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in one Coach, and follow next after the Emperour: and after then the Ladies and Gentlewomen in divers Coaches. The Archduke goes before the King, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all theſe on foote goe the Courtiers, Knights, and Imperiall Miniſters of all ſorts and condition. On both ſides walke the Guard called <hi>Hartſchierer</hi> and <hi>Trabanten</hi> bareheaded, which indeed is a brave ſight and makes a great traine.</p>
                     <p>A troupe of Souldiers on foote follow the Ladies, which attend and waite on the Emperour from his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Court till he returne, to dine at the Court or any where elſe, be it in a Monaſtery or Colledge, or any other place whereſoever.</p>
                     <p>The Popes Nuncio and other Ambaſſadours, never appeare before his Imperiall Majeſty; till after divine ſervice, or other publike acts bee done; and then they preſent themſelves to his Imperiall Majeſty, and waite upon him to his Coach, and then they preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:14"/>
When his Imperiall Majeſty is in the City, out of the Court, the City gates are all ſhut, and locked up.</p>
                     <p>The great Maſter of the horſe, doth uſe to goe with his head covered on the left ſide of the Imperiall Coach, but abroad he ſits in the Coach ouer againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
                     <p>When the Emperour goes out of his chamber to Church or Chappell, and returnes againe by the Knights great chamber and antichamber, the Pages of honour, the Nobles, Knights, Gentlemen of the chamber, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, Barrons, Earles, Princes, and other Officers of ſeverall conditions, follow them. After the Princes follow the Ambaſſadours, if any bee preſent, then the Popes Nuncio, the Archduke, the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and then his Imperiall Majeſty; and after him the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, the Queene of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Archdutcheſſe, every one with his h of maſter, and laſt of all, the Ladies of honour. The Guard of both ſorts waite till the traine be paſſed, and untill his Imperiall Majeſty be set at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, within and without the Knights chamber even to the antichamber. On Sundaies and feſtivall daies, the Trumpets uſe to ſound in the Court of the Caſtle called <hi>Burgplatz.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 5. <hi>Of the Imperiall antichamber, and of the Knights and Nobles chamber, &amp;c. and what is uſually done there.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Barons and Knights, Councellors and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Officers, Agents and others, who either have had audience of the Emperour, or who otherwiſe have acceſſe thither, untill it be time to returne home; uſe to waite in the antichamber or chamber of Knights. In
<pb facs="tcp:2122:14"/>
the roome where his Imperiall Majeſty gives audience, no man may put on his hat, but an abſolute Prince, or a Prince of tht Empire, a Cardinall, the Popes Nuncio, and Kings Ambaſſadours.</p>
                     <p>Here it is alſo to be obſerved, that when his Imperiall Majeſty is to paſſe the Knights chamber, and comes neare it, one of the huiſhers with a key raps the doore twice, for a ſigne of his Imperiall Majeſties comming. When the Emperour paſſeth the chamber of Knights, divers petitions and memorials are frequently preſented to him; and withall, he is admoniſhed and put in mind of the neceſſity and importance of the buſineſſe, which his Imperiall Majeſty moſt graciouſly receives, and gives eare unto every ones petition, although ſometimes it be very long with great patience and equanimity, without diſpleaſure or anger.</p>
                     <p>When his Imperiall Majeſty ſees any forraine Knight of ſpeciall qualities, or any who is lately returned to the Imperiall Court, whom he had knowne before, he gives him his hand to kiſſe. He willingly heares propoſitions made unto him, and moſt graciouſly anſwereth them, and ſometimes of himſelfe hee moves and askes ſome gentle and pleaſing queſtions.</p>
                     <p>He receives all writings and memorials with his owne hands, and carries them with him into his owne cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and never gives them away, untill he come thither. He uſually ſpeaketh German or Italian, and ſometimes alſo Latine, and that very readily and correctly; but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeakes French or Spanniſh, no not with the Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Ambaſſadour himſelfe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:15"/>
                     <head>CHAP. 6. <hi>Of the yearely revenewes of the Kingdomes, and hereditary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of his Imperiall Maieſty.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is difficult to ſpeake certainely of the yearely reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of his Imperiall Majeſty, out of his Kingdomes and hereditary Provinces; becauſe thoſe Countries, aſwell by reaſon of the ordinary and extraordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions, as for other cauſes are changed much from the ancient ſtate, and are very uncertaine.</p>
                     <p>His Imperiall Majeſty hath a very great revenew, from the <hi>Hungarian</hi> mines of gold and ſilver, but doth expend it all, and much more in preſerving the places bordering on the <hi>Turke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> hath long poſſeſſed the Vpper <hi>Auſtria,</hi> for twelve millions of florins payd at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> in the yeare 1622. and ſtill by that agreement it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ingaged unto him. And this at the preſent is much depopulated in divers places by the inſurrections of the boores.</p>
                     <p>The Marquiſate of Vpper and Lower <hi>Luſatia</hi> in the yeare 1636. was granted to the Electour of <hi>Saxony,</hi> for ſome millions in hereditary propriety.</p>
                     <p>The revenew of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Moravia,</hi> beſides the ordinary and extraordinary contributions and other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſome few yeares ſince, amounted about ſome three millions yearely.</p>
                     <p>The revenew of <hi>Sileſia</hi> hath beene uncertaine of late yeares, but the yearely impoſt on Beere onely, is farre above two hundred thouſand florins.</p>
                     <p>But the revenewes of Lower <hi>Auſtria, Stiria, Carinthia, Carniola, &amp;c.</hi> are of all others the moſt certaine, ſafe and
<pb facs="tcp:2122:15"/>
ordinary, and theſe according to report, amount unto about two millions of florins.</p>
                     <p>The faithfull ſubjects alſo of his Imperiall Majeſties dominions, doe yearely ſend to the Imperiall Court ſome hundred thouſand florins. The provinciall Dyets doe likewiſe helpe him to much money. And beſides all theſe, the goods which were confiſcated by reaſon of the many rebellions in <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Moravia,</hi> and in the Vpper <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and ſomewhat in the Lower, have brought above three and forty millions of florins to the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Treaſury, ſince the yeare 1618.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>Of the Empreſſe, King</hi> FERDINAND <hi>the third, the Queene</hi> MARY, <hi>Archduke Leopald William, and the Emperours daughters.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ELeonora</hi> the Roman Empreſſe, daughter of <hi>Vincent,</hi> the elder Duke of <hi>Mantova,</hi> and ſiſter to the late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Duke <hi>Vincent</hi> of <hi>Mantova,</hi> is now thirty ſeven yeares of age, of a perfect ſtature, gentle countenance, and wiſe; a good wife, liberall, mercifull, and meeke. She had for her dowry from her Ducall houſe, about three hundred thouſand crownes: And his Imperiall Majeſty hath given her lands in lower <hi>Auſtria</hi> to above that valew in exchange. When ſhe was crowned at <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> the <hi>Hungarians</hi> preſented her a hundred thouſand Rixdollers<hi>:</hi> and in the ſecond provinciall Dyet of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> eighteene thouſand Rixdollers, and another time alſo, thirty thouſand. His Imperiall Majeſty allowes her commonly every moneth two thouſand florins, (which in Engliſh is no more than three hundred pounds ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,) &amp; a Country houſe commonly called <hi>Favoritenhoff</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:16"/>
Her habit is almoſt Spanniſh, ſhe is pious and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and entertaines Eccleſiaſticall perſons with great love and honour, and chiefly Capuchins and Carmelites.</p>
                     <p>His Imperiall Majeſty hath left foure children living, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third, King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia; Leopald William,</hi> Archduke of <hi>Auſtria; Maria Anna,</hi> wife of <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and; and <hi>Cecilia Renata,</hi> who is yet unmarried<hi>:</hi> all borne of his Imperiall Majeſties firſt wife, who was his coſin german, and ſiſter to <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third is now of nine and twenty yeares of age compleat; hee is well favoured, of an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicke countenance and faſhion, of a taller ſtature than his father, blacke haire and beard, becomming his royall face, and giving it a manly forme; hee is wiſe, prudent and ſerious, carefull of his reputation, ſilent, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things like the Duke of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> He payes his debts duely, but withall, he knowes well how to practice the proverb, <hi>Ne quid nimis,</hi> or rather as the Dutch, <hi>Neere reckon'd, well payd;</hi> yet will be wanting in nothing which is juſt and decent. His ſtudies (in which he hath well profited) are fit for a King, as well neceſſary in warre as in peace, chiefly the Mathematickes, and art of warre and fortification, he ſpeakes many Languages, <hi>German, Italian, Latin, Bohemian</hi> and <hi>Spanniſh.</hi> He is devout, and religious<hi>:</hi> and he hath a particular Court of his owne.</p>
                     <p>The Queene his wife is the <hi>Infanta Mary,</hi> ſiſter of <hi>Philip</hi> the 4th. King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> whoſe dowry (the ſame with the Queene of <hi>France)</hi> was five hundred thouſand crownes, every crowne valued at thirteene ryals. The King her brother alſo was at the care and charge of her tranſport even to the furtheſt parts of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Archduke <hi>Leopold William,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Strasburg, Baſſan</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:16"/>
and <hi>Halberſtadt,</hi> is three and twenty yeeres of age, tall and of a ſtrong complexion, a lover of hunting; he hath put on the habit of a Churchman. But it is ſaid, that he will not continue in this Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, but intends to marry.</p>
                     <p>The Archdutcheſſe <hi>Mary Anne,</hi> who is now married to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> her uncle, of the age of twenty eight, well bred, devout and vertuous, prudent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, of blacke haire and eyes, of a moſt ſweet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, well skil'd in <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Italian. Vadiſlaus</hi> the now King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſhould have married her: but, they ſay, the marriage was hindred by the States of <hi>Poland,</hi> and by the Kings Counſellors; ſhee was afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi> the onely ſonne alſo of the Prince Palatine of <hi>Newburg: Albert</hi> Duke of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> as alſo <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> by the example of <hi>Sigiſmund Bather</hi> deſired to have married her; to which effect the <hi>Tranſilvanian</hi> ſent his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to his ſacred Imperiall Majeſty at <hi>Newſtat.</hi> But at laſt her uncle <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> carried her.</p>
                     <p>The yonger Imperiall Princeſſe, the Archdutcheſſe <hi>Cecilia Ranata,</hi> is five and twenty yeares old, fairer fac'd than her ſiſter, godly, vertuous, and very well brought up, but ſpeakes her Mother tongue onely <hi>German,</hi> and although ſhe underſtand <hi>Italian,</hi> ſhe ſpeakes it not. The common opinion and conjecture is, ſhe ſhall be married to the Cardinall <hi>Infant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe two Imperiall Princeſſes are of a perfect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and ſtature, and ſomewhat of a ſtrong com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:17"/>
                     <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>Of the foure chiefe Officers of the Imperiall Court, the High Steward, the High Marſhall, High Chamberlaine, and High Maſter of the Horſe, and of thoſe of the Chamber, and of their Aydes, Pages of honour, Guards aſwell horſe as foot, Court Chaplaines, and Imperiall father Confeſſour.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe higheſt and chiefeſt Office of the Imperiall Court, is the high Steward; a grave man, ſtately, and now aged, who heretofore under the Emperour <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> was high Chamberlaine.</p>
                     <p>The high Marſhall of the Court is a great and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table office of authority and reputation, whoſe juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction extends it ſelfe not onely over all the Courtiers, Officers, and others belonging to the Imperiall Court, but alſo over foraigne Agents, Reſidents, Ambaſſadours, and Deputies; ſolliciting and negotiating affaires and buſineſſes in the Imperiall Court<hi>:</hi> and over all that have any imployment at Court, workemen, Iewes, and ſuch like. His office alſo is to aſſigne lodgings to every one according to diſcretion: when the Emperour removes his Court elſewhere, except at the Electorall and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Dyets, for there the hereditary Marſhall of the Empire doth exerciſe his juriſdiction. The ſaid Court Marſhall hath his Quartermaſter, and other inferiour harbingers (commonly called Furriers) under him; who have the charge of billetting and lodgings. And his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty being abſent, the chiefe Marſhall of the Court is his Vicegerent.</p>
                     <p>Vnder the juriſdiction of the high Chamberlaine, are thoſe of the chamber, and all others ſerving therein. He conducts all Kings Ambaſſadours, and other Princes,
<pb facs="tcp:2122:17"/>
Lords, and Knights, unto their audience with his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty. He receives all letters of credence from all Agents and Soliciters, as well of forraigne Princes, as of thoſe of the Empire, and all others ſent to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Court, directed to his Imperiall Majeſty, and ſignifies the prefixed time of their audience by a huiſher of the Chamber. He often watcheth whole nights him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before the Imperiall Chamber, he weares a guilt key of the chamber, as doe the reſt of the chamber, tyed to a blacke ſilke ſtring, which is a ſigne they are of the Chamber to his Imperiall Majeſty. Thoſe of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber receive themſelves the golden key from the high Chamberlaine, and going from Court, they are bound to deliver it up to him againe; and returning backe to the Imperiall Court they receive it againe, and weare it as before. Their monthly ſtipend is forty florins (ſix pound ſterling) with their dyet at Court, as alſo have the other twelve of the Chamber in ordinary.</p>
                     <p>There are divers others alſo of the Chamber, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive neither wages nor dyet, nor ought elſe, except the guilt key, with the title and honour.</p>
                     <p>Two of the twelve of the Camber in ordinary, every weeke by turnes lie and watch all night before the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Chamber. When the Emperour eates in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichamber, they take the aſſay of the meate, which is ſerved thither. If any one be to be made of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he muſt take an oath of his allegiance to his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſty, before the high Chamberlaine, and give ſecurity.</p>
                     <p>In the abſence of the high Chamberlaine, the eldeſt of the Chamber ſupplies his Office. When his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty ſits publikely at table, the Sewers, which are truely Nobles and of ancient families (ſome of them
<pb facs="tcp:2122:18"/>
being Barons and Earles) ſerve and waite at Table, and ſo doe the Cupbearers and Pantlers, and over them all is a certaine Officer (commonly called <hi>Obriſter Staebel mey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter)</hi> who is otherwiſe one of the Chamber, who bearing a blacke ſtaffe, uſhers the diſhes which are brought to the Imperiall table; neither hath hee any certaine wages, beſides his dyet at Court. Hee uſeth alwaies to attend his Imperiall Majeſty in travelling, and hath a horſe, or a coach roome appointed for him. Of theſe and the like Nobles and Courtiers, there are about threeſcore which have onely their dyet and accommodation, as they call it, in travelling; and who remaine in Court in hope of ſome better preferment, which they ſeldome or never expect in vaine, unleſſe ſometimes their fortune be ſlow and too long comming.</p>
                     <p>His Imperiall Majeſty hath alſo ſome ſervants of the Chamber, who are by their places to hearken after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſcourſes and rumours, and theſe uſe to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of what they conceive will prove acceptable. They are honoured with Nobility and have their dyet at Court, and have alſo horſes or coach roome for tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell allowed, and ſixteene florins wages by the month.</p>
                     <p>And as his Majeſties Imperiall liberality and innate bounty towards his faithfull Servants and Courtiers is inexhauſtible: ſo he doth ſometimes according to the quality of the ſervice, reward them very liberally, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their ordinary wages, that afterwards they may more patiently expect, untill God ſhall further favour them; remembring (as it were) that the rich man who entertained his ſervants alwaies with that comfort, to reward them largely after his death, was admoniſhed by this inſcription: <hi>Give thine whilſt it is thine, which after death is none of thine.</hi> Whereupon his Imperiall
<pb facs="tcp:2122:18"/>
Maieſty about two yeares ſince ſaid to the Ieſuits, be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Fathers, you ſhall not have alwaies with you <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the ſecond.</p>
                     <p>There are likewiſe hiuſhers of the chamber, who wait at the doore of the Antichamber, and ſuffer none but thoſe who are allowed to enter there, theſe have a monthly ſtipend of twelve florins.</p>
                     <p>The great maſter of the Horſe hath authority and command over all that belong to the Stables. He helpes his Imperiall Majeſty, when he gets on horſeback. When he rides out of Towne, he ſits in the Imperiall Coach with his head covered. But when he goes to Church, he goes on foot on the left hand of the Coach, alſo his head covered.</p>
                     <p>The expence of his Imperiall Majeſty for the Stables, is great; for hee keepes ſome hundreds of horſes, of which many are ſpoyled by hunting: and beſides theſe in his hereditary Provinces, he hath many and ſtately Stables.</p>
                     <p>Part of the Pages of honour are <hi>Germans,</hi> part <hi>Italians,</hi> and <hi>Belgians,</hi> ſeldom of other Nations. They are brought up in ſtudy and the exerciſe of the body, and are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards preferred to the offices of Sewers, Cupbearers, or the like, as alſo ſome to more eminent offices, as their qualities deſerve. They hold the torches in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or Chappels behind the Prieſts, while Maſſe is ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated; their livery is of three collours, yellow, blacke, and white.</p>
                     <p>Of the Guards, ſome are horſemen or lanciers, (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Hartſhterer)</hi> and of them there are one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, in the time of the former Emperours they were nobly deſcended, ſome alſo of late have beene of noble Familes, and others expert and approved ſouldiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginſt
<pb facs="tcp:2122:19"/>
the <hi>Turke,</hi> the common enemy of Chriſtendome, in the warres of <hi>Hungary;</hi> but at this day the greateſt part are of meane condition. In Towne they waite on foote, bearing their Lances, but out of Towne as horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they are cloathed as Pages with a livery of three colours.</p>
                     <p>The Guards on foote (commonly called <hi>Trabauten)</hi> are in number one hundred alſo. Theſe waite onely in Towne with their halberds, and are, for the moſt part, tradeſmen and mechaniques<hi>:</hi> their coates and cloaths are likewiſe of three colours.</p>
                     <p>The ſixe Court-chaplaines or Deacons are all Prieſts, every morning they ſing Maſſe, and in their turnes by weekes they ſay grace before the Imperiall Table, they are little eſteemed, they have every one their dyet at Court, and three hundred florins (or 45. pound ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) wages yearely; and one of them who is the chiefe Parochus, hath foure hundred florins, beſides which they uſually enjoy ſome other Eccleſiaſticall benefices, whereby they may the better provide for their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</p>
                     <p>The Emperours Confeſſour is Father <hi>Laimormain,</hi> of the order of the Jeſuits, by Nation a <hi>Flemming</hi> or <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loone,</hi> and an old man. He hath the greateſt authority in the Imperiall Court, as he who hath the heart of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and his conſcience in his hands, and at his becke; his counſels and advices as well in Eccleſiaſticall caſes of conſcience, as in politike affaires prevaile before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and unto him they are referred. Whoſo hath this father for his Patron, may ſafely effect his buſineſſe in the Imperiall Court.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:19"/>
                     <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>Of the ſeverall Imperiall Court Counſels, as of the Cabinet Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the Imperiall Court Counſell, the Chamber Court Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, Millitary Counſell, Eccleſiaſticall Counſell, Counſell of conſcience, Hungarian Counſell, Bohemian Counſell, and confiſcation Counſell.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Privy Councellours of the Cabinet, excell the other Counſellours in dignity, for they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in conſultation of States matters, concerning the peace and warre of the Emperours hereditary King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Dominions, and the petitions and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of forraigne Kings and Princes. To theſe alſo belong all matters of the Chambers, and whatſoever is firſt debated and deliberated by other Counſels, and concluded by votes, and referred to his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. And alſo, what other Counſels have before deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Cabinet Counſell afterwards ſometimes chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth or otherwiſe diſpoſeth of, and from thence is the Imperiall reſtitution to be expected in all things.</p>
                     <p>In matters of the Empire, the judgement and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Imperiall Court Counſell, grounded on ſtrong and firme reaſons, is ſeldome rejected or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Cabinet Counſell. And hence it appeares that all things firſt come to his Imperiall Majeſty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their diſpatch; except ſmall matters, which may of courſe be granted by the Preſident of the Imperiall Court Counſell, or Vice Chancellor of the Empire.</p>
                     <p>All matters of grace, of what nature ſoever they bee, are preſented to his Imperiall Majeſty, with all humbleneſſe, and preſently they paſſe and belong unto the Imperiall Cabinet Counſell; yet ſometimes his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb facs="tcp:2122:20"/>
Majeſty cauſeth them to be referred to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Court Counſell, that he may underſtand their reformation and judgement, before he gives his owne gracious judgement thereupon.</p>
                     <p>About two yeares ſince the Prince of <hi>Eggenberg</hi> had the direction of this Cabinet Counſell, and was abſolute Patron of <hi>Caeſars</hi> will, ſo that they then had but one heart &amp; one way; as the Prince of <hi>Eggenberg</hi> within the Court had all the power, ſo the Duke of <hi>Friſland</hi> did ſway in the warres.</p>
                     <p>And although he kept his bed almoſt continually by reaſon of the gout and collicke, with which he was much afflicted, and although his houſe was a good diſtance from the Imperiall Court, yet his Imperiall Majeſty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed his Cabinet Counſell to bee alwaies aſſembled there, and himſelfe paſt to his houſe from the Archdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Caſtle, or Imperiall Court through a long Gallery, and aſſiſted in his owne perſon at the conſultations. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he onely viſit him at times of Counſell, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times alſo daily, and ſometimes often in one day. And his Imperiall Majeſty, and the Empreſſe did often uſe to play and ſport themſelves in his houſe. This Prnce was of an admirable judgement, a quicke underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, a great capacity and eloquence, and framed by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a moſt comely ſhape, a bigot in religion, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, moſt happy in adviſing and reſolving counſells; and on that knew how to ſatisfie his Imperiall Majeſty in all things.</p>
                     <p>The Emperour had mightily inriched him, and made him very great, as may in part appeare by the titles which he enioyed whilſt hee lived. It was then a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, that the Emperour had three mighty hills; to wit, <hi>Eggenberg, Werdenburg,</hi> and <hi>Queſtenberg:</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:2122:20"/>
three precious ſtones <hi>Dietrichſtein, Walſtein</hi> and <hi>Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chenſtein</hi> in his hereditary Kingdomes and Provinces; for that thoſe Families had attracted and appropriated to themſelves a great part of the beſt and faireſt domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the hereditary Provinces of his Imperall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
                     <p>But as this Prince of <hi>Eggenberg</hi> hath ſtill enjoyed the conſtant grace of the Emperour, the favour of all the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the eſteeme and praiſe of all the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Court, and a generall reſpect and honour of all the Country and Empire: Son on the other ſide, as ſoone as the treaſon of the Duke of <hi>Fridland</hi> &amp; his conſpiracy, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at <hi>Pilſen,</hi> was diſcovered, both the Emperours grace and all other mens favour and reſpect towards him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to faile<hi>:</hi> ſo that he had but even time enough, yea ſcarce enough (when the King of <hi>Hungary Ferdinand</hi> the third, taking his laſt leave of the ſaid Prince of <hi>Eggen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and bidding him farewell, without thoſe termes of kindneſſe, which otherwiſe are uſually given to Princes of the Empire) to withdraw himſelfe out of the Court, and in the beſt manner he could, make (as it were) his retreat into <hi>Stiria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of the Cabinet Counſell to the Emperour were, the Cardinall of <hi>Dietrichſtein,</hi> a <hi>Moravian</hi> by Nation; the Biſhop of <hi>Vienna</hi> of the Rhine; the Count of <hi>Megar,</hi> an <hi>Auſtrian;</hi> the Count of <hi>Trantmanſdorff</hi> a <hi>Stirian;</hi> the Count of <hi>Fugger</hi> of <hi>Suevia;</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Lilieufield</hi> a <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalian;</hi> the Count of <hi>Schlick</hi> a <hi>Bohemian;</hi> the Count of <hi>Werdenberg</hi> an <hi>Italian;</hi> Count <hi>Mansfelt</hi> an Earle of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Roman Empire, who ſeldome comes to Counſell; Count <hi>Schlawata</hi> a <hi>Bohemian;</hi> Count <hi>Kevenhuller</hi> a <hi>Carin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian;</hi> the Count of <hi>Morsburg</hi> a <hi>Franconian,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Breuner</hi> an <hi>Auſtrian.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:21"/>
The Imperiall Court Counſell next in ranke to the Cabinet Counſell, is where all affaires of the Empire both publike and private are both conſidered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided, according to the lawes and conſtitutions of the Empire, and according to the grants and charters of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and immunities of the Electours, Princes, and States of the Sacred Roman Empire, that every one may be maintained and eſtabliſhed therein; and not by any meanes be burthened, contrary to the Lawes.</p>
                     <p>The Counſellors of this Counſell are partly Nobles, and partly Doctours. Of the Nobles there are but ſixe of the Empire, the reſt are all borne in the Emperours hereditary Provinces. The Doctours are many, and moſt of them borne in the Empire; that is, within the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Provinces. And becauſe the affaires of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, Princes, and States of the Sacred Roman Empire are of great moment; therefore the conſultation and direction being made, his Imperiall Majeſty is informed thereof in his Cabinet Counſell, and from thence his reſolution is expected. Hence the diſpatches are ſent to the Secretary, and being prepared, the ſaid Secretary firſt ſubſcribes himſelfe on the left hand below, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Vicechancellour of the Empire, in the midle towards the right hand, and laſt of all his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſignes the cloze under the writing, towards the right ſide.</p>
                     <p>The yearely wages of every one of the Imperiall Court Counſellours, is twelve hundred florins, (one hundred and forty pounds ſterling) and beſides his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty diſtributes and gives them gratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according to their merit; and according as every one hath faithfully and profitably diſcharged his office on his Imperiall Majeſty.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:21"/>
The Court Counſell of warre, is compoſed for the moſt part, of Knights and Commanders. In this they doe conſult and make proviſion for the garriſons and ſouldiers, how to continue the warre and to aſſigne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary allowance to the ſouldiers, money for the armies, victuals, and proviſion; and to ſupply them with muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and all other things, directed for the good, profit, and benefit of his Imperiall Majeſty, in all things which may and ought to be done.</p>
                     <p>The Court Counſell of the Imperiall Chamber, hath not onely power and juriſdiction in all other chambers, but alſo lookes unto all the revenewes and rents aſwell of the Empire, as chiefly of his Imperiall Majeſty, his hereditary Provinces. For although every one of his Imperiall Majeſties hereditary Kingdomes and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, have a peculiar chamber, yet all of them depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid Court chamber.</p>
                     <p>The reſolutions of this chamber are ſomewhat ſlow and tedious; and thence it was, that in the Diet of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungary,</hi> this amongſt others was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a great grievance, that the States and ſubjects of that Crowne, could not obtaine diſpatch, but were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained at great expence and charges, to neglect the affaires and buſineſſes of their owne familie, to attend in vaine this Court chamber. The now preſident of this Counſell and Court chamber, is an Eccleſiaſticall Prelate.</p>
                     <p>And here it is chiefely to be obſerved, that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Court chamber, who directs ſo many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of revenewes from the Emperours hereditary Kingdomes and Provinces, whether he be depoſed or reſignes his office, is not obliged to give any account of his adminiſtration.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:22"/>
The Eccleſiaſticall Counſell was inſtituted by the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond, that Eccleſiaſticall matters and thoſe which concerne Religion, aswell in the Empire, as in his Imperiall Majeſties hereditary Kingdomes and Dominions, might be therein reſolved and deliberated. This Counſell hath neither a Preſident, nor a ſet number of Counſellours; the one halfe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is of Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and the other of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique.</p>
                     <p>The Counſell of conſcience conſiſts onely in the meeting of Eccleſiaſticall perſons, which are more or leſſe according to the occaſion.</p>
                     <p>When his Imperiall Majeſty treated the peace of <hi>Prag</hi> in the yeare 1635. with the Electour of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and his conſcience was much perplexed, whether he might any longer ſuffer the Evangelicks to enjoy the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Eccleſiaſticall goods in the Empire; for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very whereof, the warre had ſo long continued, and ſo much blood had beene ſhed: This queſtion of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of ſo great a conſequence, was refer'd to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Divines, that thereupon they might declare their judgement. Hereupon divers Eccleſiaſticall perſons were aſſembled from divers places in the City of <hi>Vienna:</hi> the Counſell was compoſed of two Cardinals, two Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, two Prelates, two Cannons, two Fathers, of every ſociety and order, (amongſt which were alſo two Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits.) And they deliberated and conſulted thereon for divers weekes, and at laſt delivered an opinion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Imperiall Majeſty did afterwards agree of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles with the Electour of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and thereupon the peace was publiſhed.</p>
                     <p>And this Aſſembly of Eccleſiaſtiques was then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the Counſell of conſcience; becauſe the matter
<pb facs="tcp:2122:22"/>
touched the conſcience of his Imperiall Majeſty.</p>
                     <p>The Court Counſell for <hi>Hungary</hi> conſiſts of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> onely, and hath a dependance on the Palatine of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who is there as Viceroy.</p>
                     <p>The preſent Palatine is the Lord <hi>Eſterhaſy,</hi> Count <hi>de Gallanta,</hi> Knight of the golden Fleece; who governes the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Kingdome in ſecular matters, as Cardinall <hi>Paſman</hi> the Ieſuit, Archbiſhop of <hi>Gran</hi> doth in ſpirituall.</p>
                     <p>To this Counſell alſo belong the affaires of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Dalmatia, Creatia</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Bohemian</hi> Court Counſell, although it ſeemes not to be a ſet Counſell, as the others, becauſe therein ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily are only a Chancellor, Vicechancellor, &amp; Secretary: &amp; that beſides the government of that Kingdom is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lieutenant and ſupreame Officers at <hi>Prag:</hi> nevertheleſſe, divers petitions and ſupplications, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching tenures, immunities, confirmations and inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Provinces, and all ſorts of feudall affaires are bought to the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Court Chancery, as well out of the City as Country, and are afterwards all diſpatched in the Court Chancery.</p>
                     <p>There is alſo a particular Officer of tenures and feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who (the vaſſals conveniently deſiring it) doth grant unto them their recognziances or atteſtations that they have performed the feodatory oath, which being brought into the Chancery, there are afterward diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the feodary patents. If there happen any proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they are firſt ſent to the Royall Counſell of appeales for information and report of their opinion therein; and afterwards they are reſolved and decided in the Court Chancery. Other appeales alſo from the whole Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> of all the cities, townes and parts thereof are brought thither and many times decrees and
<pb facs="tcp:2122:23"/>
ſentenſes, about feudall affaires are there pronounced and obteined. The Barons and Knights of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſeeke juſtice and redreſſe (if they need) at a Court called, the royall Landtable. And matters of debt are decided at a Court, commonly called, the office of the Burggrave; next in dignity to the former. Reviewes or affaires of Reviſion are referred out of the Chancery to the chamber, called the Greene chamber. When there happens any thing of moment in the Court, there is held a <hi>Bohemian</hi> Counſell at the Lord Vicechancellours of the Empire, the Baron of <hi>Stralendorfs:</hi> To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, becauſe there befall at this time divers buſineſſes of great moment, concerning the affaires both of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> as alſo the incorporate Provinces, which are to bee diſcuſſed and reſolved upon (which would have beene too troubleſome for the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Counſell alone) his Imperiall Majeſty hath deputed (beſides the ſaid <hi>Bohemian</hi> Counſellors) ſome others of the Imperiall Court Counſell, and joyned them in Commiſſion with his ſaid Vicechancellour <hi>Stralendorff.</hi> The confiſcation Counſell conſiſts of the Biſhop of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Lilienfield,</hi> Preſident of the Imperiall Court chamber, the Count of <hi>Schlicke</hi> Preſident of the Court Counſell of warre; together with the Secretary of the Court chamber, <hi>Hoffman</hi> of <hi>Ankerſon.</hi> In this Counſell of confiſcation, was taken the deliberation and reſolution about the diſtribution of the confiſcated goods and Lands of the late Duke of <hi>Fridland,</hi> Count of <hi>Kinskie,</hi> and the Baron <hi>Ilaw:</hi> and ſince that time very lately in the ſame Counſell hath beene conſulted about the diſtribution of the goods of <hi>Terskie,</hi> a great part whereof is already beſtowed on others. And this cauſe of <hi>Terskie</hi> being now finiſhed, they are now buſied in
<pb facs="tcp:2122:23"/>
cauſes of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and divers others. And theſe confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted goods amounted to many millions, beſides the three and forty millions already mentioned. Theſe and the like, are the meanes whereby the ſouldiers are partly ſatisfied, and appeaſed in their importunities.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>Of the forraigne Ambaſſadours, and Agents, and of the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours and Agents of the Empire, now at</hi> Vienna.</head>
                     <p>THe Pope hath an ordinary Nuntio to the Imperiall Court, who is called the Appertolicke Nuncio. He pretends ſpirituall juriſdiction, not onely in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with their adherent and incorporated Countries, and in all other Countries and Provinces of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> but even in the whole <hi>German</hi> Empire. He watcheth alſo for the ſafety of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that it may receive no prejudice nor detriment, and if he obſerve any ſuch thing, he oppoſeth himſelfe and proteſts againſt it.</p>
                     <p>As he did lately in the cauſe of Bremen, and was much diſpleaſed at the Emperours gracious reſolution therein: to whom his Imperiall Majeſty made anſwer, that hee was enforſed by the Treaty of <hi>Prag,</hi> to yeeld to that and many other things, becauſe the Pope had forſaken him.</p>
                     <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath his ordinary Ambaſſadour, and at this time almoſt continually an extraordinary, the Count <hi>d' Onnate,</hi> who helpes to direct and uphold the German and Imperiall Millitary forces as well with counſell as with meanes and ſupplies of money. He hath his Counſell alſo; his Counſellours are Father <hi>Chirova</hi> a <hi>Franciſcan,</hi> the Queene of <hi>Hungaries</hi> confeſſour; Doctor <hi>Novara</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and Secretary Bodin.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>French</hi> Kings emulation, and being in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency
<pb facs="tcp:2122:24"/>
with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hinders him from keeping an Ambaſſadour in the Imperiall Court. His laſt Agent was forced to retire himſelfe thence.</p>
                     <p>The King of Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> hath an Agent with his Imperiall Majeſty.</p>
                     <p>The State of <hi>Venice</hi> have heretofore had an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in the Imperiall Court, but ſince the difference about ſtyle and title, betwixt the <hi>Spanniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour, the Count <hi>d'Onnate</hi> and Signior <hi>Pietro Gritti,</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour of <hi>Venice,</hi> ſome thirty yeares ſince; there hath beene no ordinary Ambaſſadour from the State of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> in the Imperiall Court: but they have their Agent, who was invited not long ſince to diſpoſe the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, to ſend againe an ordinary Ambaſſadour to the Imperiall Court, with proffer to receive him with the like honour as is given to Ambaſſadours of Kings.</p>
                     <p>The great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> three yeeres ſince had likewiſe his Ambaſſadour there, who was received with the Title of Ambaſſadour at the Imperiall Court, and equall honour with the Ambaſſadour of <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> But now he hath onely a Secretary at <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> hath for a long time ſent no Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to the Imperiall Court, becauſe he pretends precedency, before the great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Electors, Princes, &amp; States, of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire have ſome their Reſidents, and others their Agents, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiating their affaires in the Imperiall Court, but when their happens any thing of moment or difficulty they ſend their Ambaſſadours to his Imperall Majeſty.</p>
                     <p>The Popes Nuncio takes the firſt place in the Court before all other Ambaſſadours, and before the Princes of the Empire then preſent. After him the <hi>Spanniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour claimes and pretends precedency.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:24"/>
THE STATE OF THE IMPERIALL-COVRT of the EMPEROVR FERDINAND THE SECOND.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is treated,</hi> Of all higher and lower Officers, and Miniſters, Privy Counſellors, Imperiall Court, Court-chamber, Court-Millitary, Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Bohemian, Auſtrian, and divers other ſuch like Imperiall and Royall Court-Councellors, and Court diſpatches, of the ſeverall Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and of their Officers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And principally,</hi> Of the ſeverall Iuriſdictions of the foure chiefe Court Officers: Of Ambaſſadours, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents, and Agents, Artificers, Tradeſmen and Muſicians of the Court, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As it was</hi> MDC. XXXVI.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by ANNE GRIFFIN. 1637.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:25"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:25"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>The High Steward of the Court.</head>
                     <item>THe L. <hi>Leonard Hellfried,</hi> Count of <hi>Megaw,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Cabinet Counſellours.</head>
                     <item>THe L. <hi>Francis,</hi> Cardinall and Prince of <hi>Dietrichſtein,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Olmuiz</hi> in <hi>Moravia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Anthony,</hi> Prince and Biſhop of <hi>Vienna,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Crembſmunſter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Leohard Hellfned,</hi> Count of <hi>Megaw,</hi> high Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Imperiall Court.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Maximilian</hi> Count <hi>Trantmanſdorff,</hi> high Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to K. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Iohn Erneſt Fugger,</hi> Count of <hi>Kerchburg</hi> and <hi>Weiſſenhorne,</hi> Knight, Preſident of the Imperiall Court-Counſell.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Lilienfield,</hi> Preſident of the Imperiall Court-chamber.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Henry Schlicke</hi> Count of <hi>Parſaw,</hi> and <hi>Weiſenkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen,</hi> Preſident of the Imperiall Court-counſell of warre,</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> Count of <hi>Werdenberg,</hi> Chancellour of the Imperiall Court.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Wolgang,</hi> Count and Lord of <hi>Mansfelt,</hi> Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Counſellour of the warre, and Governour of <hi>Raab</hi> in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>George Lippai</hi> of <hi>Zombor,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Veſperin,</hi> Chancellour of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Counſell.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>William</hi> Count of <hi>Schlavata,</hi> high Chancellour of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:26"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:27"/>
The L. <hi>Francis Chriſtopher Khevenhiller,</hi> Count of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenberg,</hi> high Steward of the Court of the Queene of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Iulius Neidhard,</hi> Count of <hi>Noersburg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Peter Henry</hi> of <hi>Stralendorff,</hi> Baron, Vice-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of the Sacred Roman Empire.</item>
                     <item>The L. <hi>Sigfrid Chriſtopher Preuner</hi> Baron, Lieutenant of Lower <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The High Chamberlaine.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THe Lord</hi> Iohn Iacob Khieſel, <hi>Count of</hi> Gotſher.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The high Ma ſhalt of the Court.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THe Lord</hi> Leonhard Helfried, <hi>Count of</hi> Harrach.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The high Maſter of the Horſe.</head>
                     <item>THe Lord <hi>Bruno,</hi> Count and Lord of <hi>Mansfelt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Lords of the Emperours chamber in ordinary are theſe following.</head>
                     <item>THe L. <hi>Iohn Chriſtopher</hi> of <hi>Paar</hi> Baron; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Poſt-maſter for the Court.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wentzel</hi> Count of <hi>Wurben.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles</hi> Count of <hi>Portia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Georg Achat</hi> C. of <hi>Loſenſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Szywa</hi> Count of <hi>Wurben.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Frederick</hi> Cou. of <hi>Caveriani.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hierome</hi> Co. of <hi>Montecuculi.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Montauto</hi> Co. of <hi>Mountacut.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Barthol. Khiel</hi> C. &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Frederick</hi> Co. of <hi>Atomos.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vratiſlaus</hi> Co. of <hi>Furſtenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis</hi> Co. of <hi>Picolomini.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> Co. of <hi>Swartzenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wolf Engelbrecht</hi> Co. of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wersberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diolate</hi> Co. of <hi>Conoſſa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simon Lewis</hi> Co. of <hi>Dietrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> Count of <hi>Trauſton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Ehrnrich</hi> C. of <hi>Traut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſtorf.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> Co. of <hi>Budiani.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> Count <hi>Forgatſh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:27"/>
                        <hi>Iulius</hi> C. of <hi>Salm. Barons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gabriel Ardedi</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Sigiſmund Gayler</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dioniſe Setſhy</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Staniſlaus Potaizi Wolfskie</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iacob di Negro</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William of Tedenbach</hi> Free-b.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtopher of Ebiſwald</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Maximilian</hi> Free-ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Lamberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Ernest</hi> of <hi>Molar</hi> Free-baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn George</hi> Free-baron of <hi>Herberſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Free-b. <hi>Teufel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rodolf</hi> Free-baron of <hi>Paar.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe following of his Imperiall Majeſties chamber ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, are all either Princes, Earles or Lords.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>PRince <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Caſpar</hi> Maſter of the Teutonick Order, Prince of <hi>Mergetheim.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iules Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxen Lawenburg:</hi> Collonel.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rodolf Maximilian</hi> Duke of</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saxen Lawenburg,</hi> Collonel.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Albert</hi> Duke of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Lawenburg,</hi> Collonel.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rodolf</hi> Duke of <hi>Lignitz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Wentzel</hi> Duke of <hi>Munſterberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maximilian</hi> Prince of <hi>Liech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Prin. of <hi>Cardenas. Earles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anthony Gunther</hi> Count of <hi>Oldenburg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtian</hi> C. of <hi>Waldeck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> C. of <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Frederick</hi> C. of <hi>Hardeck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Lewis</hi> C. of <hi>Swart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Frederick</hi> C. of <hi>Furstenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William</hi> C. <hi>of Slawata.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wolfgang</hi> C. <hi>of Mantsfelt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bruno</hi> C. <hi>of Mansfelt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry</hi> C. <hi>of Shlick.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maximilian</hi> C. <hi>of Dieterich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Chriſtopher</hi> C. <hi>Khe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venhuller.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iaroſlaw Borzita</hi> C. <hi>of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leonhard Hellfrid</hi> C. <hi>of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:28"/>
                        <hi>Balthaſar</hi> C. of <hi>Maradas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> C. of <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George</hi> C. of <hi>Opperſtorf.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthias</hi> C. of <hi>Gallas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Michael Adolf</hi> Co. of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theim.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Vratiſlaw</hi> C. of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trowitz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adam Paul</hi> C. of <hi>Slawata.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maximilian</hi> C. of <hi>Wallſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leonhard Charles</hi> C. of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rodolf</hi> C. of <hi>Colloredo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Octavius</hi> Co. <hi>Piccolomini. Barons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arnold</hi> Freebaron <hi>of Peymer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philip Huſman</hi> Freebaron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Iacob</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Kuſſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Erneſt</hi> Freeb. of <hi>Kollonnitſh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ferdinand Curtz</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Serftenaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtopher Loebell</hi> Freebar.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sigfrid Chriſtopher Preuner</hi> Freebaron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iulius Neidhard</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Moersburg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Leopald Nothaft</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Wehrenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gundacre</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Polheim.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paul Palfy</hi> Freebaron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Steven Palfy</hi> Freebaron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Erneſt</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Suys.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paul Iacob</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Starenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rodolf</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Tief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenbach.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Frederic</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtopher Thonradle</hi> Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtopher Paradiſer</hi> Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sigiſmund Adam</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Traun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> Freebar. of <hi>Wallſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Tzhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Henry</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Stralendorf.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conrad</hi> Baron of <hi>Steinberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry</hi> Freebar. of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iulian.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Teuffell</hi> Freebaron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> Freebaron of the <hi>Reck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leopold</hi> Freeb. of <hi>Stralendorf.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioachim Adolf</hi> of <hi>Stralendorf</hi> Baron.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Imperiall Court-counſell hath two Benches, whereof the one is called, the Bench of the Nobles, and conſiſteth of Counts, Barons and Knights, to the number of twenty.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:28"/>
The other Bench is called the Bench of the learned Counſellours; whereof are ten, moſt of them Doctours or Batchellours both of the civill and canon Law.</item>
                     <item>The Preſident of this Court-counſell is <hi>Iohn Erneſt Fugger</hi> Count of <hi>Kirchberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Another Counſell, called the Imperiall Court-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, conſiſteth of ſeven Counſellors, which are either Freebarons, Barons, or Doctours: <hi>Ignatius Abbot</hi> of <hi>Lilly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> is the Preſident of this Counſell.</item>
                     <item>The Counſell of Warre conſiſteth of eight Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, whereof is one Duke, two Counts, and five Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barons: and <hi>Henry</hi> Count of <hi>Shlick</hi> is Preſident of this Imperiall Military-counſell.</item>
                     <item>The Captaine of the Guard with Javelins (conſiſting of one hundred horſe and called Hartſhier) is <hi>Don Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar</hi> Count <hi>de Maradas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Captaine of the foot, or Halberdiers, is <hi>Philip</hi> Count of <hi>Mansfelt,</hi> and this Guard conſiſteth alſo of one hundred men.</item>
                     <item>The Maſter of the Staffe, or the Imperiall Officer, who bearing a blacke rod, uſhereth the meat which is carried to the Imperiall table, commonly called Stab-maſter, is <hi>Diodato</hi> Count <hi>de Conoſſa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bruno</hi> Count of <hi>Mansfelt</hi> is now both Maſter Falkner and Huntſman; the two offices of the high Hunter and high Falkner.</item>
                     <item>The generall Poſtmaſter is <hi>Iohn Chriſtopher</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Paar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>At the Imperiall Court are alwaies as Counſellors for the affaires of <hi>Hungaria, George Lippai</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Veſperin,</hi> Court-chancellour for that Kingdome, and <hi>Thomas Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kulich</hi> of <hi>Brukonoz</hi> Counſellour of that Kingdome, and Lieutenant of the Kings perſonall preſence in judgment.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:29"/>
In like manner are Counſellours for the affaires of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia:</hi> Namely, <hi>William</hi> Count of <hi>Slawata</hi> ſupreme Chancellour, and <hi>Adam Libſtentzkie of Kolobrat,</hi> Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baron and Vice-chancellour of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>After the ſupreme Maſter of the ſtaffe or <hi>Stabmaſter,</hi> follow the ordinary Court offices: in which are</item>
                     <item>Three Cup-bearers: the eldeſt whereof at this time is an Earle, the other are Barons.</item>
                     <item>There are two Maſters (called Chamberlains) of the plate, whereof the firſt Chamberlain is <hi>Iohn George,</hi> Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baron of <hi>Herberſtein.</hi> The ſecond or under Chamberlaine is <hi>Laurence</hi> Lord of <hi>Huttendorf.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The chiefe Maſter of the Kitchin is <hi>Theodore Hartman</hi> of <hi>Clarſtein.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Eccleſiaſticke perſons.</head>
                     <item>FAther <hi>William Lamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi> Ieſuit, Imperiall confeſſour: and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties conſcience.</item>
                     <item>Two Court Preachers, one for the <hi>German,</hi> the other for the <hi>Italian.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paul Knor</hi> of <hi>Roſenroth,</hi> chiefe Chaplaine of the Court, and great Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</item>
                     <item>There are ſeven other Court-chaplaines.</item>
                     <item>An Imperiall Library-keeper.</item>
                     <item>An Imperiall Hiſtorian.</item>
                     <item>And there was one, but now is no Mathematician to his Imperiall Majeſty.</item>
                     <item>The Treaſurer is <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Churland.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Court Phyſicians of his Imperiall Majeſty are five.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Reſidents and Agents, now preſent at the Imperiall Court, are</head>
                     <item>FOr the King of <hi>Spaine, Ambroſius Reutz,</hi> who negociates alſo for <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:29"/>
                        <hi>Mounſier de Scarbonniere,</hi> Agent for the K. of <hi>France,</hi> did of late negotiate at the Imperiall Court at <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> but a few months ſince he was not onely prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but in a few daies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, totally to leave the City.</item>
                     <item>The Agent for the Qu. Mother, <hi>Mounſier Roverie,</hi> is returned to his Queene.</item>
                     <item>The King of <hi>England</hi> his Agent M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The K. of <hi>Polands</hi> Agent, <hi>Mounſ. Gibboni.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Agent for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick of <hi>Venice, Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt Balderino.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of <hi>Savoy, Octavius Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logneſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the Republicke of <hi>Genua, Peter Panicall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The D. of <hi>Mantua</hi> hath no body at the Imperiall Court.</item>
                     <item>The D. of <hi>Modena</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gociates his affaires by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Agent.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Vnder the High Stewards Iuriſdiction.</head>
                     <item>ONe Controller.</item>
                     <item>One Cofferer, called</item>
                     <item>Fenning-maſter.</item>
                     <item>One Huſhier.</item>
                     <item>Five Heralds.</item>
                     <item>One chiefe ſurveyor of the Tapeſtry.</item>
                     <item>Two Porters of the great chamber.</item>
                     <item>One ſervant of the Cloſet.</item>
                     <item>Three ſervants for the Plate.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Court kitching.</head>
                     <item>ONe Cooke for the month.</item>
                     <item>Six Maſter-cookes.</item>
                     <item>Ten Under-cookes.</item>
                     <item>Two Baſters, or Roſters.</item>
                     <item>Two helpers, or aſſiſtants.</item>
                     <item>Two Broth-cookes, or for boyled meat.</item>
                     <item>Two helpers, or boylers.</item>
                     <item>Eight Kitchin-boyes.</item>
                     <item>Two Kitchin-porters.</item>
                     <item>One Kitchin dore-keeper.</item>
                     <item>One Woodman, or cleaver of the wood.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:30"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Court Cellar.</head>
                     <item>ONe Court Cellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man called chiefe Butler.</item>
                     <item>One clerke of the Cellar.</item>
                     <item>Two ſervants of the cellar.</item>
                     <item>Three coopers of the cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</item>
                     <item>Two children of the cellar.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Court Larder.</head>
                     <item>ONe Kitchin clerke.</item>
                     <item>Two Purveyers.</item>
                     <item>Two keepers of the meat.</item>
                     <item>Two carriers or porters.</item>
                     <item>One Court burcher.</item>
                     <item>One Chandler.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Table Coverers.</head>
                     <item>TWo chiefe coverers of the free Tables.</item>
                     <item>Two chamber table-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers.</item>
                     <item>Two preparers or coverers of the Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men waiters table.</item>
                     <item>One coverer of the Pages Table.</item>
                     <item>Two coverers of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers tables.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Landreſses.</head>
                     <item>ONe Landreſſe for the body.</item>
                     <item>One for the mouth.</item>
                     <item>One for the table; and</item>
                     <item>One for the Kitchin.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The high Chamberlaine his juriſdiction, or thoſe which ſerne in the Chamber.</head>
                     <item>TEnne ſervants of the chamber.</item>
                     <item>Two chamber doore-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</item>
                     <item>One fire-maker for the ſtoves.</item>
                     <item>Foure Guards of the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, vulgo <hi>Trabanten.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:30"/>
One chiefe Ieſter named <hi>Ionas Schiſſel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Three other jeſters or fooles.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Offices ſubject to the high Marſhall of the Court his Iuriſdiction.</head>
                     <item>ONe Court Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter.</item>
                     <item>One Secretary of the high Marſhals Court.</item>
                     <item>Six Harbingers, vulgarly called Furriers of the Court.</item>
                     <item>Three Meſſengers, vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Einſpanninger, ſerving on horſe-backe.</item>
                     <item>Two guards of the office vulgarly called Marſhals Trabanten.</item>
                     <item>Two Court Chirurgions.</item>
                     <item>All Agents in the Imperial Court of the Electours, Princes and States of the Sacred Roman Empire.</item>
                     <item>All and every Court nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatours, artificers and tradeſmen, the number of them exceeds one hundred and fifty.</item>
                     <item>All the free Iewes of the Court.</item>
                     <item>One Lieutenant of the cheſſe, vulgarly Provoſt.</item>
                     <item>One Sergeant.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Vnder the chiefe master of the Horſe his juriſdiction, are</head>
                     <item>Twenty Imperiall Pages of honour, with their governour and tutor.</item>
                     <item>One Maſter Avenor.</item>
                     <item>One clerke of the Avery.</item>
                     <item>Two Horſe-riders.</item>
                     <item>Two Colt-breakers, vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly called Paſtin and Klepper-riders.</item>
                     <item>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Overſeer.</item>
                     <item>Foureteene Court Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petters.</item>
                     <item>One Kettle-drummer, vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Heerpaucker.</item>
                     <item>One Maſter Fencer.</item>
                     <item>One charger of pieces, vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly called Buchſenſpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who prepares the Guns to be diſcharged.</item>
                     <item>Two yeomen of the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop.</item>
                     <item>Two black or horſe ſmiths.</item>
                     <item>Sixteene Footmen.</item>
                     <item>One Tentmaker<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:31"/>
One Maſter of the Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</item>
                     <item>One Maſter of the Litters.</item>
                     <item>One Sadler for the Court-ſtables.</item>
                     <item>One Boot-cleanſer.</item>
                     <item>Eight and twenty Grooms or Horſe-keepers in the Spanniſh ſtable.</item>
                     <item>Six and twenty Groomes or Horſe-keepers in the ſtable for hunting nags,</item>
                     <item>Ten ſervants of the Litters.</item>
                     <item>Two Coach-men of the Emperours Coach.</item>
                     <item>Foure and twenty Court Coach-men.</item>
                     <item>Six and twenty Poſtillons</item>
                     <item>Six boyes of the Stable.</item>
                     <item>Ninty great ſaddle Horſes, fit for warre, and warlike exerciſes.</item>
                     <item>Foureſcore amblers, and hunting Horſes for the Emperours perſon.</item>
                     <item>Threeſcore Coach-horſes.</item>
                     <item>Two and twenty Mules.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Vnder the Captaine of the Horſe-guard, are theſe Officers.</head>
                     <item>A Lieutenant.</item>
                     <item>A chiefe Furrier.</item>
                     <item>An inferiour Harbinger.</item>
                     <item>One hundred Hartſhiers or Horſemen.</item>
                     <item>Three Trumpetters.</item>
                     <item>One Chirurgion.</item>
                     <item>One Black-ſmith.</item>
                     <item>One ſervant of the Guard.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Vnder the Captaine of the Foot guard, are theſe.</head>
                     <item>ONe Gentleman har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binger.</item>
                     <item>One under Harbinger.</item>
                     <item>One hundred Souldiers, (called Trabanten) with Holbards.</item>
                     <item>One Drummer.</item>
                     <item>One Fifer.</item>
                     <item>One ſervant of the Guard.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Theſe following perſons are join'd as Commiſſioners to the Imperiall Privy Counſell.</head>
                     <item>THe Baron of <hi>Queſtenberg,</hi> and <hi>Bohemian</hi> affaires.</item>
                     <item>Commiſſioner for <hi>Italian</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2122:31"/>
D. <hi>Iuſtus Gebhard</hi> Counſellor of the Imperiall Court, and commiſſioner in matters concerning the laſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Prag.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matthias Arnoldin,</hi> of <hi>Clarſtein</hi> Counſellour of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Court and principall Secretary of State.</p>
                  <p>D. <hi>Iohn Soldner</hi> Counſellor of the Imperiall Court, and Secretary of the Imperiall Court-counſell.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Now followeth the ſeverall Chambers of the Court Chancery.</head>
                     <item>THe chamber for the Diſpatches of the Privy-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, whereof are <hi>Matthias Arnold</hi> of <hi>Clarſtein,</hi> before mentioned; and alſo D. <hi>Iohn Soldner</hi> a civilian, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Theſe have their owne clerkes and ſervants expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the diſpatches, and if they need more, they uſe the help of the clerks of the Imperiall chancery.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The chamber of the Imperiall Court-chancery for the affaires of Germany.</head>
                     <item>ALthough D. <hi>Iohn Soldner</hi> is Counſellour of the Imperiall Court, and hath in the ſaid counſell his owne voice and ordinary vote, and being moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly buſied in more ſecret diſpatches, for which cauſe <hi>Paul Thomas</hi> (who is otherwiſe an Inditer of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Court chancery) ſerveth in his ſtead in the ſaid Court Imperiall counſell for enrolling: Nevertheleſſe the direction of the court Diſpatches in the Empire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill in his hands.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bartholomew Immerdorffer</hi> Imperiall counſellour, Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Court-receiver.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Friſinger</hi> Imperiall Counſellor and Taxer for the diſpatches.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Dieterlin</hi> Regiſter of the Court of chancery.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fra. Katſemayer</hi> Vice-ſecretary of the Court-chancery.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:32"/>
                        <hi>Chriſtopher Switzer</hi> enroller of the Court-chancery.</item>
                     <item>Foureteene clerkes and ingroſſers.</item>
                     <item>One ſervant of the Chancery.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Chamber of the Latin diſpatch of the Imperiall Court-counſell.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IOhn Walderode</hi> Imperiall</item>
                     <item>Counſellor and Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of the Imperiall</item>
                     <item>Court counſell.</item>
                     <item>Foure clerkes and ingroſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</item>
                     <item>One keeper of this Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery chamber.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Chamber of the diſpatches of the Court chamber.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>BArtholomew Shoellhard</hi> Imperiall Counſellor and Commiſſioner or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendarius of the Court-chamber.</item>
                     <item>There are three Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this Court-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Theſe Diſpatches chiefely concerne confiſcated goods and now belong to the Confiſcation Counſell, wherein the principall Commiſſioners, are</head>
                     <item>THe Biſhop of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Abbot of <hi>Lilien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and</item>
                     <item>The Count of <hi>Schlick.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Item one Regiſter.</item>
                     <item>One aſſiſtant to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter.</item>
                     <item>One Diſpatcher of the Court chamber.</item>
                     <item>One Aſſiſtant.</item>
                     <item>Seven Inditers.</item>
                     <item>Nine Clerkes.</item>
                     <item>Five ſervants of the Court chamber.</item>
                     <item>One Dorekeeper of the Court counſell chamber.</item>
                     <item>One Meſſenger of the Court chamber.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Chamber of the Military Court Counſell, or Counſell of warre.</head>
                     <item>THere are of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell foure Secretaries.</item>
                     <item>One Regiſter.</item>
                     <item>One Aſſiſtant to him.</item>
                     <item>One Diſpatcher.</item>
                     <item>One Aſſiſtant to him.</item>
                     <item>Six Clerkes.</item>
                     <item>One porter or dorekeper.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:32"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Chamber of the Court Marſhals office.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>LEonhard Fleuner</hi> Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Counſellor, and Secretary of that office.</item>
                     <item>He hath his owne clerkes and ſervants.</item>
                     <item>In matters of conſequence there are joyn'd to him by the Court Marſhall, ſome Counſellors of the Imperiall Court, with the Fiſcall of the ſame court.</item>
                     <item>Two Guards of the Court Marſhals office.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Of the Hungarian Counſell Chamber, are</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>LAurence Ferenskie</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor both to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and to the King of <hi>Hungaria;</hi> and Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Counſell.</item>
                     <item>One Taxer for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches.</item>
                     <item>One Regiſter, and</item>
                     <item>Two Clerkes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Of the Bohemian Counſel-chamber, are</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>GEorge Freiſleben</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor both to the Emperour, and to the K. of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> &amp;c. and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Counſell.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wolf Henig</hi> Taxer and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of both the Counſels of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>One diſpatcher.</item>
                     <item>Two Inditers.</item>
                     <item>Six Clerkes; the yongeſt whereof is alwaies oblig'd to be Porter.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Chamber of the Court Counſell of Auſtria.</head>
                     <item>THe Counſell &amp; Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery! of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutchy of <hi>Auſtria</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by <hi>Iohn Baptiſta</hi> Count of <hi>Werdenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>It hath two Secretaries.</item>
                     <item>One Regiſter and Taxer.</item>
                     <item>One Inditer.</item>
                     <item>One Diſpatcher.</item>
                     <item>Five Clerkes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:33"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Imperiall Court Muſicke.</head>
                     <item>ONe Maſter of the Court-chappell.</item>
                     <item>Two Organiſts.</item>
                     <item>Twenty Inſtrumental Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Vocall Muſicians.</head>
                     <item>SEven Baſes.</item>
                     <item>Seven Tenors.</item>
                     <item>Five Altus.</item>
                     <item>Foure Deſcants.</item>
                     <item>Eleven Muſicall Trumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</item>
                     <item>Three Trumpetters not Muſicall.</item>
                     <item>One Kettle Drummer.</item>
                     <item>Item twelve boyes and ſchollers with a Maſter.</item>
                     <item>One Notiſt.</item>
                     <item>One keeper of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                     <item>One Inſtrument maker.</item>
                     <item>Two inſtrumental ſervants.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Beſides theſe there are of the Imperiall Muſicke, and belonging thereto in number about foureſcore perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:33"/>
                  <head>THE ORDINARY STATE of the Court of her Imperiall Majeſty of the Roman Empreſſe, ELENORA, &amp;c. Borne Ducheſſe of <hi>Mantova</hi> and <hi>Monferrat,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <head type="sub">How the ſame was kept, and ſerved by all high and low Officers, Ladies, Mayds of honour, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, Mayds, and Servants.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>In the Imperiall reſidence at</hi> Vienna, <hi>in the laſt yeere.</hi> 1636.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aximilian</hi> Prince of <hi>Dietrichſtein</hi> is high Steward of the Court of the Empreſſe.</item>
                     <item>Lady <hi>Vrſula,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Atomos</hi> Shee high Steward of the Court.</item>
                     <item>Lady <hi>Agnes</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Farens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach,</hi> is Governante of the Court Ladies.</item>
                     <item>The Ladies or Mayds of honour of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, are thirteene; being all Mayds, and daughters to Earles.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vrban</hi> Freebaron of <hi>Potnig</hi> is Steward of the Court of the Archdutcheſſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Lady <hi>Cecilia Renata,</hi> ſecond daughter to the Emperour.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Margaret</hi> Baroneſſe of <hi>Heberſtein</hi> is Governante of her Court: She hath but foure Ladies or Mayds of honour, all daughters to Earles and Barons.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:34"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>Servants and Officers of the Empreſſe her Court.</head>
                     <item>One of the Guard.</item>
                     <item>ONe <hi>German</hi> Secretary.</item>
                     <item>One <hi>Italian</hi> Secretary.</item>
                     <item>One Confeſſour.</item>
                     <item>Three Court-Chaplaines. <hi>Afterwards.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Six ſervants of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</item>
                     <item>One Wardrobekeeper.</item>
                     <item>One Taylor.</item>
                     <item>One Apothecary.</item>
                     <item>Two of the Cellar.</item>
                     <item>One dore-keeper of the chamber.</item>
                     <item>One fire-maker of the chamber.</item>
                     <item>One porter of the great chamber.</item>
                     <item>Two guards of the chamber</item>
                     <item>Two cookes.</item>
                     <item>One footman.</item>
                     <item>One coverer of the Ladies tables.</item>
                     <item>Two coverers for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the chamberers and mayds.</item>
                     <item>Six Taylors for the maids.</item>
                     <item>Item ſix Chamber-maids.</item>
                     <item>Two other mayd-ſervants.</item>
                     <item>One miſtreſſe Woman-cooke.</item>
                     <item>One inferiour Shee-cook.</item>
                     <item>Nine Ladies Waiting-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</item>
                     <item>One Chamber-woman.</item>
                     <item>One Landreſſe for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:34"/>
                  <head>THE STATE OF THE COVRT of the Archduke <hi>Leopald William</hi> of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> the Emperours ſecond ſonne.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ebaſtian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Gurch,</hi> Privy Counſellor both to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and to the Archduke <hi>Leopald William,</hi> is alſo this Archdukes high Steward and Chamberlain.</item>
                     <item>Three Privy Counſellors, whereof the laſt is a Ieſuite, and his Confeſſour, the two others are Freebarons.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Iacob</hi> of <hi>Daun,</hi> Knight of the Teutonick order, is Maſter of his horſe.</item>
                     <item>There are five Gentlemen of his chamber, the one being an Earle, and the foure others all Freebarons.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Pacher</hi> Imperiall Counſellor for Lower <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> is his Court-chancellor.</item>
                     <item>One Doctor of Phyſick, by name, <hi>Leonhard Mulgieſſer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Michael Ottho</hi> Biſhop, Secretary.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Officers of his Chancery.</head>
                     <item>ONe Regiſter.</item>
                     <item>One Expeditor or diſpatcher.</item>
                     <item>Two Clerkes.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:35"/>
One Aſſiſtant.</item>
                     <item>One ſervant or chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Beſides.</head>
                     <item>There are fourteene Pages all children to Freeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of quality.</item>
                     <item>Six Groomes, or ſervants of his Bedchamber.</item>
                     <item>Six Footmen.</item>
                     <item>Other officers and ſervants that waite on him, are (as it were) borrowed of the Emperours Court.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:35"/>
                  <head>A CATALOGVE OF THE PRINCES, ELECTORS, and States of the Sacred German Empire. <hi>Anno</hi> M. DC. XXXVI. The Electors of the Sacred Roman Empire.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Eccleſiaſtickes.</head>
                     <item>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> Arch-chancellor of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Roman Empire through <hi>Germany.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> Archchancellor of the ſacred Roman Empire for <hi>Italie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Tryer</hi> Archchancellor of the ſacred Roman Empire for <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Arelate.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Secular Electors.</head>
                     <item>THe King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Arch-cupbearer of the Sacred Roman Empire.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:36"/>
The Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> Arch-Sewer of the Sacred Roman Empire.</item>
                     <item>The Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> Arch-Marſhall of the Sacred Roman Empire.</item>
                     <item>The Marquiſſe of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> Arch-Chamberlain of the Sacred Roman Empire.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Archbiſhops of the Sacred Roman Empire.</head>
                     <item>MEniz.</item>
                     <item>Collen.</item>
                     <item>Tryer.</item>
                     <item>Magdenburg.</item>
                     <item>Saltzburg.</item>
                     <item>Bremen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Biſhops.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Ausburg.</item>
                           <item>Aichſtat.</item>
                           <item>Bramberg.</item>
                           <item>Baſel.</item>
                           <item>Biven.</item>
                           <item>Constance.</item>
                           <item>Chur, <hi>or</hi> Coire</item>
                           <item>Cammerach.</item>
                           <item>Freyſingem.</item>
                           <item>Hildeſheim.</item>
                           <item>Halberſtat.</item>
                           <item>Liege.</item>
                           <item>Lubech.</item>
                           <item>Munſter.</item>
                           <item>Minden.</item>
                           <item>Oſnabrug.</item>
                           <item>Paſſaw.</item>
                           <item>Paderborne.</item>
                           <item>Ratzenburg</item>
                           <item>Regensburg, <hi>or</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Ratisbonne.</item>
                           <item>Strasburg.</item>
                           <item>Schwerin.</item>
                           <item>Spire.</item>
                           <item>Tryer.</item>
                           <item>Verdun.</item>
                           <item>Wartzburg.</item>
                           <item>Worms.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The three Biſhopricks of</hi> Metz, Theul, <hi>and</hi> Verdun <hi>were taken from the Roman Empire by the Kings of</hi> France, <hi>and are detained to this day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The maſter of the Teutonicke order, Prince of</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getheim, <hi>is indeed no Biſhop, but an Eccleſiaſticke Prince of the Empire, and takes the firſt place after the Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The ſecular Princes of the Sacred Roman Empire.</head>
                     <item>ANhalt, <hi>Princes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Bavaria,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Brunſwick <hi>and</hi> Lunenburg, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Brandenburg, <hi>Marqueſſes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Baden, <hi>Marquiſſes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>By</hi> Rhine, <hi>Palgraves.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Holstein, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Heſſen, <hi>Landgraves.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Lorraine, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:2122:36"/>
Leuchtenburg, <hi>Landgraves.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Meckelburg, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Oſtereich <hi>or</hi> Auſtrian, <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dukes of the</hi> German, <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the</hi> Burgundian <hi>line.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Pomerania, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Saxonia, Gullick, Cleveland, <hi>and</hi> Bergen, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Saxonia <hi>of</hi> Engem <hi>and</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falia, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Savoy, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Wirtenberg, <hi>Dukes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>The</hi> Lithuanian <hi>and</hi> Ratzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian, <hi>are alſo received amongſt them, and put in the number of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Empire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Abbots, Priors, and Prelates.</head>
                     <item>COrvey.</item>
                     <item>Elwangen.</item>
                     <item>Elchingen.</item>
                     <item>Fulda.</item>
                     <item>Gengenbach.</item>
                     <item>Hirſhfelt.</item>
                     <item>Keyſerſheim.</item>
                     <item>Kempten.</item>
                     <item>Merchthall.</item>
                     <item>Munchrot.</item>
                     <item>Murbaco.</item>
                     <item>Munſter <hi>in the</hi> Gregorian <hi>vale.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Oxenhauſen.</item>
                     <item>O denheim.</item>
                     <item>Peterſhauſen.</item>
                     <item>Ritterſhauſen.</item>
                     <item>Reckenburg.</item>
                     <item>Richenaw.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>S.</hi> Emmeran <hi>at</hi> Ratisbonne.</item>
                     <item>Salmanſwile.</item>
                     <item>Shluſſenried.</item>
                     <item>S. Vlrick <hi>in</hi> Augſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</item>
                     <item>S. Cornelius Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</item>
                     <item>Stabe l</item>
                     <item>Veſin <hi>or</hi> Irſee.</item>
                     <item>Vſperg.</item>
                     <item>Weingarten.</item>
                     <item>Wettenhauſen.</item>
                     <item>Wenden.</item>
                     <item>Abbateſſes.</item>
                     <item>BVchaw <hi>on the Lake called</hi> Federſea.</item>
                     <item>Eſſen.</item>
                     <item>Guttentzel.</item>
                     <item>Gerenroda.</item>
                     <item>Hervord.</item>
                     <item>Heggenbach.</item>
                     <item>Lindaw.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Vpper Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in</hi> Ratisbonne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Lower Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at</hi> Ratisbonne.</item>
                     <item>Quedlingburg.</item>
                     <item>Rottenmunſter.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Earles of the Sacred Roman Empire.</head>
                     <item>BArbey <hi>and</hi> Muh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingen.</item>
                     <item>Bentheim.</item>
                     <item>Bruckhorſt.</item>
                     <item>Caſtell.</item>
                     <item>Erbach.</item>
                     <item>Eberſtein.</item>
                     <item>Furſtenberg.</item>
                     <item>Falkenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Hohenloe.</item>
                     <item>Hanaw <hi>of</hi> Munt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenberg.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:37"/>
Hanaw, <hi>of</hi> Liech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg.</item>
                     <item>Iſenburg.</item>
                     <item>Lippa.</item>
                     <item>Lewenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Leyningen.</item>
                     <item>Mansfelt.</item>
                     <item>Montſort.</item>
                     <item>Manderſhied.</item>
                     <item>Naſſaw Catzenelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bogen.</item>
                     <item>Naſſaw Sarbrucken</item>
                     <item>Neumar.</item>
                     <item>Oſtfrieſland.</item>
                     <item>Oldemburg.</item>
                     <item>Oetingen.</item>
                     <item>Ortemburg.</item>
                     <item>Ruepfen.</item>
                     <item>Solms.</item>
                     <item>Suliz.</item>
                     <item>Sayn.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The foure Counts of the Empire.</head>
                     <item>SWartzenburg.</item>
                     <item>Stollberg.</item>
                     <item>Schaumburg.</item>
                     <item>Schwartzenberg.</item>
                     <item>Tubingen.</item>
                     <item>Waldeck.</item>
                     <item>VVittigenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Wildt <hi>and Count of the</hi> Rhine.</item>
                     <item>Wied.</item>
                     <item>Zimmern.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Freebarons, Barons and Lords of the Sacred Roman Empire.</head>
                     <item>FLeckenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Fugger.</item>
                     <item>Griechingen.</item>
                     <item>Graveneg.</item>
                     <item>Hohen Geroldſegg.</item>
                     <item>Hohenfels.</item>
                     <item>Konigſegg <hi>of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendorf <hi>and</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtetten.</item>
                     <item>Limburg, <hi>heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Cupbearer of the Sacred</hi> Roman <hi>Empire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Maxelrein.</item>
                     <item>Pappenheim, <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Marſhall of the Sacred</hi> Roman <hi>Empire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reuſſen <hi>of</hi> Plawen.</item>
                     <item>Seniſheim.</item>
                     <item>Shoenburg.</item>
                     <item>Schenck <hi>of</hi> Traut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg.</item>
                     <item>Wallburg, <hi>heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Sewer of the Sacred Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wolfſtein:</item>
                     <item>Winnenberg <hi>and</hi> Peilſtein.</item>
                     <item>Waldbotten <hi>of</hi> Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenheim.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Cities of the Sacred Roman Empire.</head>
                     <item>AAch, or Aaken.</item>
                     <item>Augsburg.</item>
                     <item>Aalen.</item>
                     <item>Biberach.</item>
                     <item>Buchhorn.</item>
                     <item>Buchaw, <hi>on the lake cald</hi> Federſea.</item>
                     <item>Bingen.</item>
                     <item>Bopfingen.</item>
                     <item>Conſtance <hi>on the Lake called</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſea.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:37"/>
Colmar.</item>
                     <item>Collen on the Rhine.</item>
                     <item>Cammerich.</item>
                     <item>Dinkelſpiel.</item>
                     <item>Dortmund.</item>
                     <item>Donawert, <hi>which at this day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes not the liberties of an Imperiall City, but is detained by the Houſe of</hi> Bavaria, <hi>but is to be reſtored.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Eſligen.</item>
                     <item>Francfurt <hi>on the Maine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fridberg.</item>
                     <item>Goſlar.</item>
                     <item>Gemund <hi>in</hi> Swa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben.</item>
                     <item>Giengen.</item>
                     <item>Giengenbach.</item>
                     <item>Hervorden.</item>
                     <item>Hailbrun.</item>
                     <item>Hall in Swaben.</item>
                     <item>Hagenaw.</item>
                     <item>Iſna.</item>
                     <item>Kaufbeuren.</item>
                     <item>Keyſersberg.</item>
                     <item>Kempten.</item>
                     <item>Landaw.</item>
                     <item>Leutkirchen.</item>
                     <item>Lindaw.</item>
                     <item>Lubec.</item>
                     <item>Munſter <hi>in the</hi> Gregorian <hi>vale.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mulhauſen <hi>in</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringia.</item>
                     <item>Memmingen.</item>
                     <item>Norimberg.</item>
                     <item>Nordlingen.</item>
                     <item>Nordhauſen <hi>in</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringia.</item>
                     <item>Offenburg.</item>
                     <item>Oberenheim.</item>
                     <item>Pfullendorff.</item>
                     <item>Popfingen.</item>
                     <item>Regensburg <hi>or</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisbone.</item>
                     <item>Rotweil.</item>
                     <item>Reutlingen.</item>
                     <item>Ravensburg.</item>
                     <item>Rotenburg <hi>on the</hi> Tauber.</item>
                     <item>Roſheim.</item>
                     <item>Strasburg.</item>
                     <item>Spire.</item>
                     <item>Sweinfurt.</item>
                     <item>Schletſtat.</item>
                     <item>Turckheim.</item>
                     <item>Weinſheim.</item>
                     <item>Weiſſenburg <hi>in</hi> Nortgaw.</item>
                     <item>Wangen.</item>
                     <item>Weill.</item>
                     <item>Wimpfen.</item>
                     <item>Weiſſenburg <hi>on the</hi> Rhine.</item>
                     <item>Worms.</item>
                     <item>Weizler.</item>
                     <item>Vlme.</item>
                     <item>Vberlingen.</item>
                     <item>Zell <hi>on</hi> Hammerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:38"/>
                  <head>RELATION OF THE preſent State of the Imperiall Chamber of the Sacred Roman Empire, at <hi>Spire. Anno</hi> M. DC. XXXVI.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne Iudge of the Imperial Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</item>
                     <item>Three Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the Imperiall chamber.</item>
                     <item>One Aſſeſſour for the Electour of <hi>Mentz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>One Aſſeſſour for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of <hi>Collen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>One Aſſeſſour for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of <hi>Tryer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Two extraordinary Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſours of the Eccleſiaſtick Electours.</item>
                     <item>One Aſſeſſour for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour Palatine.</item>
                     <item>One Aſſeſſour for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>One Aſſeſſour for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Two extraordinary Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſours for the ſecular Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours.</item>
                     <item>Two <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Aſſeſſours.</item>
                     <item>Two <hi>Burgundian</hi> Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours.</item>
                     <item>Foure Aſſeſſours for the Circle of <hi>Franconia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Foure Aſſeſſours for the Circle of <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Foure Aſſeſſours for the Circle of <hi>Swaben.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Foure Aſſeſſours of the Upper Circle of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> two places whereof are now voyd.</item>
                     <item>Foure Aſſeſſours of the Lower Circle of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> all which places are now voyd.</item>
                     <item>Foure Aſſeſſours for the
<pb facs="tcp:2122:38"/>
Circle of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>One Fiſcal advocate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Doctour in Law.</item>
                     <item>Fourteene Advocates, all Doctours of Law.</item>
                     <item>One Fiſcall Procuratour Doctour of both lawes.</item>
                     <item>Two and twenty procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours, all Doctours and Licenciats in Law.</item>
                     <item>One chiefe ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Chancery, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of both lawes.</item>
                     <item>Three Protonotaries, the firſt and ſecond places whereof are now voyd.</item>
                     <item>Foure Readers.</item>
                     <item>One Fiſcall Notary.</item>
                     <item>One Regiſter.</item>
                     <item>Foure Notaries.</item>
                     <item>One Maſter of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers.</item>
                     <item>One Phyſitian.</item>
                     <item>Two Sergeants.</item>
                     <item>One receiver of the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery.</item>
                     <item>Foure Engroſſers.</item>
                     <item>Two Copiers.</item>
                     <item>One keeper of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery chamber.</item>
                     <item>Tenne Meſſengers of the Chancery, that ſerve on horſe-backe.</item>
                     <item>Ten Foot-poſts or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers ſerving on foot.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2122:39"/>
                  <head>A Catalogue of all ſuch perſons, which by his Imperiall Majeſty (during the time of his raigne) have beene created Princes, Earles, Barons or Lords.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>And first he created Princes of the Empire.</head>
                     <item>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Rneſt <hi>Count of</hi> Schaum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Iohn George <hi>Count of</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen-zoler <hi>of</hi> VVoldſtein.</item>
                     <item>Francis <hi>and</hi> Maximilian <hi>of</hi> Dieterichſtein.</item>
                     <item>Philip Ottho <hi>Count of the</hi> Rhine.</item>
                     <item>Stenko Adelbert <hi>of</hi> Lobco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witz.</item>
                     <item>Albert <hi>Duke of</hi> Fridland.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Princes and Marquiſſes of the Roman Empire.</head>
                     <item>PEter Aldobrandin <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fabritius Caraffa <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Charles Spinelli <hi>Marquis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Anthony Biglio <hi>Marquis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Charles Emanuel <hi>of</hi> Gore <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Charles Philibert <hi>of</hi> Eſte <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ludwig Victorius <hi>Marquis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ierome Caraffa <hi>Marquis of</hi> Monte-negro, <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Count of</hi> Contecroy <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Charles <hi>of</hi> Cardenas <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Paul Ierome <hi>Marquis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Anthony <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Vienna <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>George Oſſomilimius <hi>in</hi> Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Albert Altovite <hi>Marquis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Thomas Raggio <hi>Marquis.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Follow the new created Earles or Counts of the Empire.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THe Freebarons of</hi> Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaim, <hi>now Earles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Freebaron of</hi> Nachot.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Barons of</hi> Meggaw.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:39"/>
                        <hi>The Baron of</hi> Bronkorſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Baron of</hi> Geraldine.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Lord</hi> Michna.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Tilly.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Mittrowitz.</item>
                     <item>Maximilian of Trautmanſtorf.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Baron of</hi> Loſenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Iacob Kiſſell.</item>
                     <item>Balthaſar <hi>of</hi> Thanhauſen.</item>
                     <item>N. <hi>of</hi> Taxis.</item>
                     <item>Sdenko <hi>of</hi> Shambach.</item>
                     <item>Seſyma <hi>of</hi> VVr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>by.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Baron</hi> Rodrigo Barragan.</item>
                     <item>Iaſpar Bernhard <hi>of</hi> Rechberg.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> VValdeck.</item>
                     <item>Herman Tſhermi.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The two brothers of</hi> Crat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen.</item>
                     <item>Burian Bercka.</item>
                     <item>Adam Erdman Terzka.</item>
                     <item>VVilliam Verdugo.</item>
                     <item>Paul Andrew <hi>of</hi> Wolkenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Henry Erbtruchſas, <hi>Freeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of</hi> VValdpurg.</item>
                     <item>VVilliam <hi>of</hi> Mihinitz.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Iacob Erbtruchſas.</item>
                     <item>Gotfrid Henry <hi>of</hi> Pappenheim.</item>
                     <item>VVentzel <hi>of</hi> VVurben.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> VVrzowitz.</item>
                     <item>Rodolf Tertzka.</item>
                     <item>VVoldemar Chriſtian <hi>of</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain.</item>
                     <item>Theodoric <hi>and</hi> Iohn Andrew <hi>of</hi> Aurſperg.</item>
                     <item>Philip Adam <hi>of</hi> Cronberg.</item>
                     <item>Charles Chriſtopher <hi>of</hi> Brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Dorrings.</item>
                     <item>VVilliam <hi>of</hi> Clenowa.</item>
                     <item>N. <hi>of</hi> Konigſegg.</item>
                     <item>N. <hi>of</hi> Atthimis.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Balthaſar <hi>&amp;</hi> Sigiſmund Ludovic <hi>of</hi> Dieterichſtein.</item>
                     <item>Ladiſlaus <hi>of</hi> VValdſtein.</item>
                     <item>Henry Holka.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Altringer.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Charles <hi>of</hi> Schonburg.</item>
                     <item>Ioachim <hi>of</hi> Mettich.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Ludovic Iſolani.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Wolkenſtein.</item>
                     <item>Adolph <hi>and</hi> Charles <hi>of</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaim.</item>
                     <item>Nicolas des Fours.</item>
                     <item>Iacob Kuen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Hutzfeldes.</item>
                     <item>Francis <hi>of</hi> Vlefelt.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Goetz.</item>
                     <item>Iohn <hi>of</hi> Ligniville.</item>
                     <item>Theodore Trivultius.</item>
                     <item>Francis <hi>and</hi> Baptiſta Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentii.</item>
                     <item>Charles <hi>of</hi> Gaulz.</item>
                     <item>Iacob Strozzi.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Baptiſta <hi>of</hi> Verdenberg.</item>
                     <item>Henry de Ravero.</item>
                     <item>Sdenco <hi>of</hi> Collobrat.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:40"/>
Paul Bernhard <hi>of</hi> Font aines.</item>
                     <item>Vincent Cavalli.</item>
                     <item>Martin <hi>and</hi> Georg Kraſichi.</item>
                     <item>Ioachim <hi>of</hi> Quincey.</item>
                     <item>Iaſpar Erneſt <hi>and</hi> Gerard <hi>of</hi> Donhof.</item>
                     <item>Maximilian <hi>of</hi> Gallian.</item>
                     <item>Lupus Walter Zapata.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Theſe following were created Freebarons: called Liberi Barones.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THe</hi> Virnemonds, <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Reiffenberg.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Ulm.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Wrzeſwitz.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Webers.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Stein.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Toettenbeckes.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Wattſen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Sickingen.</item>
                     <item>Herman Iſherin.</item>
                     <item>Kurtzen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Benzenaw.</item>
                     <item>Spiering.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Cloſen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Meſpelbrun.</item>
                     <item>Vincent Muſhinger.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Newhaus.</item>
                     <item>Otto <hi>of</hi> Noſtitz.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Herſan.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Rorbach.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Wanſheim.</item>
                     <item>Leuin <hi>of</hi> Mortagni.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Weichs.</item>
                     <item>Rodhaubt.</item>
                     <item>Vrban Shatzel.</item>
                     <item>George Zdiarskie <hi>of</hi> Zdiar.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Wurtenbach.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Degenfelt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Queſtenberg.</item>
                     <item>Ferdinand Geitzk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fler.</item>
                     <item>William <hi>of</hi> Clenowa.</item>
                     <item>Thomas <hi>of</hi> Lindlo.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Vlric Schafgotſh.</item>
                     <item>Ioachim <hi>of</hi> Donnersberg.</item>
                     <item>Henry <hi>of</hi> Ginandis.</item>
                     <item>Iohn of Shonſtein.</item>
                     <item>Henry Charles of Orſcalor.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Huſman.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Charles Fuchs.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Altringer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Baumgartner.</item>
                     <item>Charles of Heim.</item>
                     <item>Francis Marzoni.</item>
                     <item>Vlric of Ronm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g.</item>
                     <item>Iohn of Bremd.</item>
                     <item>Cornelius of Muhlen.</item>
                     <item>Alexander of Vehlen.</item>
                     <item>Iaſpar of Gram.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Comargo.</item>
                     <item>Theodoric <hi>and</hi> Iohn Andrew of Aurſperg.</item>
                     <item>William <hi>and</hi> Werner of Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garten.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Vlric <hi>and</hi> George Ehrn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich of Puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2122:40"/>
Iohn Charles, <hi>and</hi> Otto Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick <hi>of</hi> Shonburg.</item>
                     <item>Philip Hector <hi>and</hi> Leopald <hi>of</hi> Adelſhauſen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Cloſen</item>
                     <item>Ferdinand Rodolf Laſhanskie.</item>
                     <item>Henry <hi>and</hi> Chriſtopher Adam <hi>of</hi> Muggenthal.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Fridecick <hi>and</hi> Iohn Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine <hi>of</hi> Pentzenaw.</item>
                     <item>Eberhard Adolph <hi>of</hi> Muggen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thall.</item>
                     <item>Thobias of Haubitz.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Henry Nothaft.</item>
                     <item>Francis Maximilian of Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehe.</item>
                     <item>Iohn of Reck.</item>
                     <item>George Frederic of Standing.</item>
                     <item>Iacob Brechtold.</item>
                     <item>Iohn George of Seebach.</item>
                     <item>Sebaſtin Wietz.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Gotz.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Rodolf of Bredaw.</item>
                     <item>Reinhard of Walmerode.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Chriſtopher <hi>and</hi> Iohn Paul of Ruppen.</item>
                     <item>Luther of Buwinghauſen.</item>
                     <item>Maximilian of Goltz.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Paar.</item>
                     <item>Foppius <hi>and</hi> Aiſema.</item>
                     <item>Iohn of Leutterſheim.</item>
                     <item>Corpus.</item>
                     <item>Iohn de Werth.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Reinach.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Crafts, <hi>brothers.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Barons or Lords.</head>
                     <item>Florian, Theodorich.</item>
                     <item>Albert Clodomir Fabriani.</item>
                     <item>Wolfgang William Laminger.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Baptiſt Werda.</item>
                     <item>Henry Baradas.</item>
                     <item>Chriſtoph. Nicolas, Andrew, &amp;c. Orlick.</item>
                     <item>Martin Somogie.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Baptist Trecho.</item>
                     <item>Leo Groppello Medici.</item>
                     <item>Erneſt of Suis.</item>
                     <item>Ioſeph of Neuhaus.</item>
                     <item>Erneſt of Linden.</item>
                     <item>Iohn of Merode.</item>
                     <item>Iohn William Arnold of VVachtendank.</item>
                     <item>George of Gaillard.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Cerboni.</item>
                     <item>Degenhard Bertram of Lohe <hi>in</hi> VViſen.</item>
                     <item>Iacob Francis Beſtacalda.</item>
                     <item>Matthias Gallas.</item>
                     <item>Philip <hi>and</hi> Bernhard of Arey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaga.</item>
                     <item>Francis Porta.</item>
                     <item>Adrian of Enckefort.</item>
                     <item>Erneſt, Henry <hi>and</hi> Gotfrid of of Sharenberg.</item>
                     <item>Matthew of Vernier.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
